you
And for the final time, good evening and welcome to Edinburgh, hosting the diving events at the Glasgow 2014 20th Commonwealth Games.
Big wave.
I think the mascot's a bit scary, but everybody else seems to like him, so maybe a mouth-killer on this one.
As we prepare for two more finals, the two last finals of the week at the Royal Commonwealth Ball.
By the time we get underway, by the time we get to the 10 metre later, all the seats will be taken.
There will be a raucous atmosphere in here.
Plenty of support.
Three Englishmen in the men's 10 metre.
Three English women and one Scotswoman.
in the three meter springboard to come up next.
Been an interesting week.
Not always gone to plan, not always gone to the script.
But we have 12 to go in the women's three meter springboard final.
We have 11 to go in the men's 10 meter platform final alongside me as ever to cast his eye and give us the intricacies of every dive and whether it's good, bad or indifferent.
is the Athens 2004 10 meter platform, Synchro Silver Medalist, Leon Taylor.
At this point, I always ask you that rather innate question, which you deal with so brilliantly.
What are you expecting?
Well, I'm expecting some diving, and I would like to see some high-class, world-class diving here at the Commonwealth Games.
We saw, as we usually see in the prelims, we see a mixed bag, and some athletes on their game, others still to find theirs, and of course quite a spread through the marks.
There we are, the crowd warming up.
And there's Grace Reed going in the women's three-meter final.
She dives number three, just 18 years old, her second Commonwealth Games.
And when she takes to the board, the crowd certainly show their support.
The atmosphere is great.
You can see the shots of the... Well, that's actually the diving board.
And that is the board that they're going to be diving up.
That's a close-up at the end of the three-meter springboard.
It's... Yeah.
complicated, technical, you need timing, coordination, strength, power, agility.
And that's just to do the very basic of dives.
And as we've seen over the last couple of days, a decent hurdle step helps, doesn't it?
Yeah, hurdle step is the approach to the end of the diving board on some of the dives.
So a forward and a reverse normally need a hurdle step.
That's where you walk down the diving board.
You push the diving board down with one foot.
And then you leap onto the end of the diving board, not over the end, but the end of the diving board, ideally, with two feet.
Gives you the best shot.
best shot at performing the dive.
And what we're going to be seeing is five dives performed by each of the ladies.
Five different groups of dives.
And here is the start list.
So Chung will go first.
The first of the English divers, Rebecca Gallantry, up second, then Grace Reed.
Wait for a huge cheer when they come out on pool deck for her.
she will get a massive reception and last to go looking for a notable double here after winning the one meter Jennifer Abel watch out for Madison Keeney has the chin we're going to get a couple more medals for Australia best placed after the prelims of the English Divers was Hannah Starling what an absolute pre-cursor to what's going to happen later with the 10 meter
platform which was of course Leon's event with individually and synchro wise and on paper it's very easy to just say well it's Tom Daly against Matthew Mitchell isn't it the Olympic bronze medalist from 2012 against the Olympic gold medalist from 2008 bit more to it than that
Yeah, maybe.
I still think it's going to be a head-to-head, though.
So, yeah, there will be a fight for the bronze, I'm sure.
But I'm going to tip up.
Yeah, we've got some...
VA VIPs in the crowd tonight, as you can see.
Welcome, one and all.
These were the golden tickets sold out within a matter of minutes, I think, because of the number of seats.
Still many people to take their seats, but it is very, very warm, I can assure you.
I'm sitting here in my shorts and my flip-flops, and I'm still very warm.
Here come the girls.
Actually no need for the buckets, babe, but thank you for bringing it anyway.
Three-meter individual.
for the women.
Will it use them one by one?
Three English divers, one from Scotland.
Two from Malaysia, three from Australia.
And three from Canada.
First up, Chun-Yong Chung of Malaysia.
There's Rebecca Gantry, the first that we'll see of the English Divers from the Sydney Leeds.
There's Grace Reed.
Loving this.
This is her home pool.
Got a lot of home support.
Born in Edinburgh, training in Edinburgh.
What do they say about Pamela Ware that made her react like that?
I'm not quite sure.
And El-Smith will go next.
Then Davita Sabri on Malaysia.
Alicia Black up next in position seven.
N. Yang Lee in eight.
Hannah Starling fourth after the prelims this morning.
Esther Chin.
We'll go two from the end.
Madison Keeney, she gets it right.
She'll put pressure on the winner for this morning.
The best from this morning.
There's Jennifer Able of Canada.
That's our one to 12 in the dive order.
Remember, five rounds for the win.
There'll be six rounds for the men when we get to the 10 meter platform almost immediately afterwards.
And Jennifer Abel going for a notable double here.
Silver medalist four years ago.
Gonna go one better in Delhi.
From Delhi to here.
Just a jockey position.
Yeah, royalty in tonight.
I think there will be a lot of dignitaries from various political parties in tonight as well.
It's the hottest ticket in town, even hotter than some of the Edinburgh Festival tickets, which is just getting underway in the city.
Goes on right the way through until the end of town.
So it's a bit of an overlap here.
Commonwealth Diving and the Edinburgh Festival.
which might be why the pubs and bars were rather busy last night.
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the officials for this session.
Your referee is Cathy Seaman.
Assistant referee Victoria Tomlinson.
Judge 1, Annalisa Free.
Judge 2, Kelvin Chong.
Judge 3, Valerie Beddow.
Manish, thank you very much indeed as we introduce the judges for the women's three-meter springboard.
And here they are.
And Alicia Marwood.
John McChong, Valerie Beddow, Marco Palazzo.
And then Beverly Boys, the former Canadian diver.
Now judge will go number six.
And the fate of the 12 divers to come is very much in their hands.
See how they interpret the dives.
We'll have five rounds of dives.
There'll be a lot of similar ones, like, for example, Chong Jun Xiong, who goes first, will do the inward two-and-a-half somersaults.
The dive will also be performed in a slightly different way by Grace Reed, and then by Annabelle Smith, Dr. Sabri, En-Yang Yi,
Hannah Starling, Esther Chin and Jennifer Abel.
So pretty much half or more than half of the divers will go for, in technical terms, cool of 405b, translates into an inward two and a half somersault.
So they go in reverse order.
So 12th place finish goes first and the best of the morning will go last.
And that's Jennifer Abel who's going for a notable double here.
So the advantage of diving last is that the judges tend to expect the best dives to come at the last bit of the round because you were the winner of the preliminary.
So the momentum of the competition can often carry the higher marks being awarded to the divers at the back end of the field.
But it doesn't always go that way, but sometimes it does.
Here we go.
Competition is underway.
Referee's whistle blown, so we can have our first diver on the board.
That is Cheong Kyung of Malaysia with an inward two and a half somersaults.
Well, Cheong would have been looking for a stronger start than that, leaving the dive short of vertical.
Takeoff looked OK.
It's a difficult dive to do, so you need to squeeze into that pipe shake, which she does, just letting go of her legs a little bit too early, leaving the dive marginally short of vertical.
let's see what she gets if you're looking for sevens really and 6.5 is what she gets so kind of mid-range really seven and above very good six and a half and below not quite so good getting six and a half and sixes probably not going to be challenging for the upper echelon of this event Rebecca Gantry much further down and her quality normally shows that was the morning
That can be parked and we'll start all over again with a forward two and a half semisaults, one twist for Rebecca.
Nice one, Rebecca, just allowing the dive to roll over as she goes into the water.
She's back from the end on the takeoff, which means she has to shift her weight forward in order to complete the dive.
And that affects the entry.
So she rolls over a vertical and will only score six and a halfs, I think, rather than her preferred eights, which would have been ideal opening.
Yeah, 57 it is.
Six and a half doesn't quite get the seven she wanted or above.
Six and two, six point fives.
Six and second for the time being.
Now it's the raw to greet Grace.
Grace Reed on the board.
Now she's doing a slightly different version of the inward two and a half semisoles.
This one with Tuck, not with Pike.
Consequently, it's not worth three point zero.
It's worth two point seven.
It's kind of where her program dictates she is at the moment.
Well, that's a beautiful opening round dive once again from Grace.
As Bob mentioned, opting for the slightly easier inwards.
So this is the tuck position, bending at the hips and at the knees, grabbing hold of the shins, squeezing tight, straight up and down, lowered a group of difficulties that we'll see here, probably at the bottom of the leaderboard so far.
However, another consistent dive from Grace.
Hardly put a foot wrong.
Say the degree of difficulty nowhere near as high as it needs to be to challenge for the medals.
Unless everybody drops off, but she'll be able to do what she's capable of doing at this stage.
And she's done it very well.
56.7.
Keeps her in the mix.
Pamela Ware, 21 years of age from Canada.
Introduced to diving by her dad.
Ice hockey, ice cream bet it was.
Oh, beautiful opening bank dive.
Fabulous entry into the water.
This is where the marks are awarded.
The takeoff is good.
Pike shape could do with squeezing in a little tighter.
A little bit of an arch as she goes in.
And that's an improvement on her preliminary effort.
And that should see her top of the leaderboard so far.
Only four divers in this final so far.
Bronze medalist of the 2013 World Championships in Barcelona.
I don't know if she has a pedigree to make her way through so further down the standings than we thought she would be this morning, but that can easily be reversed and has been in quite a few competitions this week.
She got off to a shaky start this morning, did Annabelle Smith.
She would like to rectify all that.
Start all over again with an inward two and a half somersaults with Pike.
You know this dive by now and you will see it several more times.
3.0 degree of difficulty for her.
Well, that's a little bit better than this morning.
Thought on a takeoff, she was backing away from the diving board a little bit too much, which can affect the rotation.
But she manages to get after it, driving those hips up and over, ducking her chin slightly as she moves past vertical into the water.
She'll be up to 3.0.
She'll get her over 60 points.
63, to be precise.
Easy calculation to make.
777 will all count towards the total.
Multiply that by the degree of difficulty gives you 63.
That's her opening dive just in behind Pam Ware.
In terms of the standings but early days yet five rounds and some bigger dives still to come.
Tabitha Sabri of Malaysia.
Once again the inward two and a half.
nice i was very impressed with this young 15 year old she has some dives later on in her list which she tends to struggle a little bit more with but this was a corking opening in the prelims she's just allowed that to go over as she's entered the water so it won't be quite as impressive as it was earlier but still she'll be one to watch and only 15 63 puts right alongside annabelle smith
seen by the judges as precisely the same dive in terms of quality.
Alicia Black goes for something different.
This will be again a 3.0 dive so the degree of difficulty the same but this is a forward two and a half somersaults with one twist for the second of the English divers we'll see in the final.
Oh, what a dive from Alicia, opening up her final.
Now, I was just on the poolside with her coach, Edwin.
And he said, yep, she's actually feeling under the weather, but you wouldn't tell from that.
She's got maybe something she's eaten or anything, so she's really struggling with her energy.
So this is going to be a long start, a long competition for her, but look at that to kick off with 70.5.
Well, whatever she's done this afternoon has worked.
Maybe she's got a bit of sleep, feeling a bit restored and refreshed.
70.50.
Nice job by Alicia Black.
Yen Li from Malaysia up next.
And we're back to the inward two and a half again.
Best we've seen so far of those.
Pamela Webb and Sabri and Smith.
Lisa Black though, first to go over 70 in this first round.
Very, very nice, well executed from Yang Yi.
So we're getting to compare and contrast this, even two and a half in the pike position.
This will get over 65 points, I think, finishing higher, keeping the splash down than her teammate, just two before her.
Sabri, this is the slightly older, more experienced Yang Yi.
And she, heavily strapped on her tricep, which is not uncommon, goes into second place.
By Delicia Black.
On to Hannah Starling, who will have a big smile.
We'll see in a moment.
It's not from that angle, obviously, but when we go front on, her smile has now just disappeared as she gets her game face on and gets ready to start the Inward 2.5 Sevensorts.
The best play start of the English this morning, but of course the points do not get carried forward.
3.0 to remind you.
Inward 2.5 Sevensorts.
Oh, good.
Very good from Hannah.
This morning, she just probably, like a lot of the girls, a little bit tired.
Got water in her ears there as she comes up.
This is a really strong attack to take off.
Squeezes into that pike shape.
Yeah, it's straight up and down.
Probably a little bit low on the water for more than a seven, but we shall see.
And we'll find out now.
Three sevens, 63.
Joint fourth, a group of 63s coming together.
Three more to go.
Three best divers from this morning up next.
Hester Chin.
She went to Sydney in the year 2009.
And she will also be doing the dive that you've seen a lot of.
All around the coast, 63 to 67 marks so far.
She better that.
No, I think she is a little short of vertical.
To better that, she will be around about 60 points.
Takeoff is OK, but she backs away from the diving board a little bit too much, which leaves her short of vertical as she goes into the water.
So the judges will penalise.
Mr Chin will be further down the leaderboard.
Yeah, only 61.5.
So six and a half and sevens for Esther Chin on that 3.0 dive.
Now onto the New Zealand Bourne, but now Australian Madison Keeney.
She is certainly one to watch here.
She was on the one.
So she is in the three, not quite so expansive on the three in terms of what she can do.
Back two and a half sevens with Pike, 3.0 for the Australian.
Just washing over as she goes into the water back two and a half somersaults in the pike position All of the girls will use a back two and half most of them in the pike position the difference here is Madison jumps through the roof She is so powerful only 18 years old Incredible job on the one meter.
She really does set herself apart Letting a falter on the entry causes the marks to be low
63 which matches what Starling, Smith, Sabri and now Keeney on 63.
Now this is the class act of the field in terms of what she's done in the past and what she did this morning.
Silver medal from Delhi.
Already got the one meter title under her belt.
Here's Jennifer Abel with her in with two and a half somersaults.
Yep, she's silver medal four years ago, a gold medal last night in the one meter springboard.
And here she is on her favorite three meter top qualifier, ready to open up her campaign.
It's steady, steadfast.
She has done it better.
So we will see where her head is and where she's at this evening.
Church Five didn't like it very much, but sevens and a 7.5 for Jennifer.
End of the first round of five of the three-meter springboard for women.
That's how it looks.
Alicia Black at the top.
Only person to go over 70 in the first round.
Lovely start.
Eng Yan Yee in second place.
A couple of Canadians tied for third.
And Grace Reed, as we mentioned, does have a lower degree of difficulty for the majority of the program.
So not expected to keep up with the more established performers.
But if you get middle of the pack, it'll be a great achievement.
Round two of the three-meter springboard for women.
Chunheng snuck in in 12th place.
We did get rid of two this morning but she got in in 12th with a forward three and a half.
Yeah, has a little bit of difficulty with this in training.
So what's so good in the preliminaries and she's missed it again in the final for three and a half in the tuck position, bending at the knees, bending at the hips in the tuck shape, just holding on to that touch shape a fraction too long, over rotating, missing her entry.
So all in all, not that great, but six point fives.
It's an OK return for Zhong Zhong.
of Malaysia.
54.60 for that.
Gold with Alicia Black in the three meter synchro.
Made a senior debut ten years ago for Great Britain.
She is for England with a reverse two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Yes, that's a good dive from Becky.
This is the one that sometimes can get away from her.
She has a tendency to pull the dive over.
This time, she waits.
Let's go at the correct time.
Little bit of a back arch, little bit of an over rotation.
So she probably won't get more than a seven, which is a shame because the height on that dive is excellent.
Oh, hang on.
Oh, dear.
He took the cameraman out there.
Most unfortunate, actually more important, the cameraman took her out there, Rebecca Caventry.
Grace Reed.
Smile when she got onto the board.
Now it's a studded concentration.
2.8 on this one.
It's with Tuck and rather with Pike.
Forward three and a half somersaults for the Scots girl.
She is just rising to the occasion, low on the degree of difficulty, yes, but high on the consistency.
Unfaltering under the expectation of this home crowd in a home pool, home country.
And she certainly takes that forward three and a half on and does a great job.
Doesn't she just?
Sevens, never shabby.
And 58.8 will put her right alongside Rebecca Gallantry at the moment.
Certainly another one of our emerging divers for the future.
Pamela Ware currently third.
That's where she finished in Barcelona at the World Champs last year.
Forward three and a half for her.
Well, she's got a point to prove.
She's coming out and attacking every one of these dives, not holding back at all.
It's an example.
You really need to get after this.
It's 3.1 degree of difficulty for a reason.
It's difficult.
You need the height.
If you get it right, if you get sevens, you're going to get mid-60s.
So 65, 66.
And that's what she'll be looking for.
Exactly.
65.10.
Look on her face.
So maybe she expected more either from the judges or maybe of herself there, but 65.
That's just a game face.
You reckon?
Game face.
Yeah, I know well.
She'd be one for the Pope, wouldn't she?
There you go.
You've already played her at some point.
Did she fleece you?
Annabel Smith with a reverse two and a half somersaults with pike 3.0 for the Australian.
Well, leaving the dive short and vertical there went wrong on the takeoff.
If you listen carefully, you won't be able to hear it on the replay, obviously, but she stamps the diving board.
She's not on the end.
So there's a miscoordination with the diving board.
The diving board is your friend.
You need to treat it nicely.
So go down with it, and then it'll fling you up in the air.
If you stamp it, it'll flick you off.
And that's what happened to Annabel.
There you go, technical talk.
Yeah, really.
People pay a lot of money for those channels.
5.5s across the board.
49.5 for Annabel Smith.
Davita Sabri for Malaysia.
Goes with the forward three and a half somersaults with Pike currently in fifth place.
It's a good dive.
This is her favored movements, the forward and the inward that she opened up with in the first round.
A little bit back from the end of the diving board, so making it hard work, but she does hang on just about long enough to get it in.
So this was good in the prelims, not quite as good in the same final because of the falter on the takeoff.
Maybe the 15-year-old from Malaysia will start to slip away now as she moves towards the weaker part of her program.
Yes, she did lead at one stage this morning, but not going to be leading here.
55.80, not a great return on that dive for Davitas Avery.
Alicia Black is our current leader.
Only person in the first round to go over 70 points.
Now, wouldn't it be nice if she could back that up
With her back, two and a half somersaults, 3.0.
Needs 60 to be in front of Pamela Ware.
And we know that she's more than capable of getting 60 on this dive.
So a little soft in her body.
She went into the water, arching through the back.
So swing in the arms, takeoff looks okay.
I did mention in round one that she isn't very well.
Now she looked a little weak on the takeoff there and a little soft on the way out of the dive.
It looked like hard work.
So I'm hoping she's got enough energy for the next three dives.
Rubbing her eyes, she looks a little bit, yeah.
So it's tough.
Put herself through that.
She doesn't look at all well, does she?
It's second for the time being after that.
Heng Yan Yee of Malaysia.
Currently ranked two.
She was after the first round with Alicia Black leading.
It's her forward three and a half with 3.1 in the pike position.
So quite a high tariff dive for her.
Phoebe well executed as well.
Classy effort.
from the older Malaysian.
Ying Yi, 21, is three in the final.
Chiang opening up.
She's the first diver.
This is one of her hardest dives, or the hardest dive by way of degree of difficulty.
3.1.
She's done a good job.
They'll be high 60s, and she goes into the lead.
Yeah, not quite 70, but very close to her.
68.20, and she does go into the lead with her 7.5 and 7s.
And Hannah Starling and Esther Chin, who will follow her, will all be going with the same dive.
So a degree of difficulty just up a notch to 3.1.
Hannah just preparing herself for her four and three and a half somersaults currently in fifth place.
72 will take her into the lead.
Oh, it's very good.
I'm not sure whether that will be good enough to get over 70 points.
It is 3.1 degree of difficulty.
She does go up, up and away.
into the water.
It's a little bit low.
She ends up short, but then ducks ahead and ends up going over.
So the judges might penalise her quite heavily for that.
Let's wait and see.
Yeah, I think they have.
Well, they've certainly taken a mark off 6.5, 6.5, and 6.5 will count.
Remember, those marks with lights through them do not count the overall score.
And 60.45 is what she received for that.
Third place now.
Now the big three from this morning.
That's the chin up first.
Same dive once again.
We'll see something different from Madison Keeney after this.
Well, what a beauty, an absolute beauty.
Esther slightly further down after her first round dive than we would expect.
Now, this will rocket us straight up the leaderboard.
It's 3.1.
We've seen it before.
If it gets close to 70 points or over 70 points, she's going to leapfrog a few of her fellow competitors.
And she does.
Yes, she has done just that.
69.75, three 7.5s.
And at the moment it's Malaysia one, Australia two.
With Yanyi in first place.
Madison Keeney of Australia.
Now, this is not the dive, so next time she has a little problem with 63.
She got in the first round, reversed two and a half somersaults with Pike, second time round.
She does so well hurdle step was a little bit off.
She's leading.
So that's the approach to the end She's leading too far forward.
She's right on the corner of the board, but look at the height She gets you must be able to see that at home.
It is incredible Especially that she's corner boarding which is so where you landed the corner of the board It's not very easy to do anything from there Let alone a reverse two and a half in the pike position and she managed to get seven and a half's on it Wow
She was virtually up in that Glasgow logo behind her.
That's how high she went.
7.5 across the board, 67.5.
And the moment she is in third place, but that may well change, could change, is likely to change with Jennifer Abel up next, the one meter champion.
Always keeps her game face on, a game head on for the evening.
looked very good this morning so that's a worry for everybody else back two and a half somersaults with Mike to finish round two of the three meter springboard yeah nice very nice indeed from Jennifer gold last night will it be gold again tonight so far it looks as though she is very much in the hunt
for another gold medal, just allowing the dive to tip over slightly at vertical.
So I think it might get eight.
Kept the splash down nicely.
A couple of eights and a 7.5 and not quite in the lead at the moment, but very, very close to it.
Very tight at the top, as you'll see in a moment when we reveal the leaderboard at the end of round two, which looks like this.
and Yan Yi of Malaysia first, able than the two Australians.
And the English diver on the front page at the moment is Hannah Starling in sixth, then Alicia Black, and Annabel Smith.
Just at the moment, not cast and drift, but at the bottom of the pile, Grace Reed for Scotland in ninth, along with Rebecca Gallantry.
Chong Yong of Malaysia is currently ranked 11th.
and she has opted to go because the choice is the divers in which order they take these dives for a back two and a half semisaults with pike which will be done by annabelle smith and a couple of the other divers in this round well jun looks so she's a little bit
Well, I'm not sure, a little bit tired.
Not quite got a competition head on.
She is much, much better than this.
She only just qualified for this final.
We lost two ladies this morning in the prelims.
And I expect much better from Chung.
She is a better diver than this.
Still, seven's good.
But when she gets it right, she can really, really get it right.
You know have some outstanding dives in the first four days here, but that wasn't one of them, but wasn't too bad three sevens Like a gallantry joint night after the second round and this one will be a forward three and a half somersaults with pike or the city of Leeds diver Terrific dive from Becky
Gold medal in the three metre synchro.
That's a good forward three and a half in the pike position.
Punching a hole in the water by grabbing the hands, she goes in.
You see the sprays on the surface of the water there, that's worth mentioning.
That's to disturb the surface of the water so the divers know exactly where the surface is because if there are no sprays, no agitation on the surface of the water, all the divers can see is the bottom of the pool.
So just that little bit of spray gives you an exact idea where the surface is so when you grab your hands just before going in, you know where it is.
A few of you have asked that question and Leon has answered it for you.
Grace Reeds forward two and a half, seven salts, one twist for the Scottish diver, 3.0, one of her bigger tariffs.
Beautiful dive.
For two and a half, one twist, 3.0.
Lots going on.
Going to get the rotation into the one and a half somersaults.
There's the one twist.
Then complete the extra somersault to make it two and a half somersaults.
It's Grace's best dive of her program so far.
That'll get 62, 63.
Any advance?
No, we're staying on 63.
Three sevens.
Good.
Nice and solid.
178 points already for her.
You don't expect a medal from Grace.
It would be far too much to expect with the degree of difficulty she's got.
But certainly looking for a middle of the pack finish if she can achieve it.
Pam Ware now for Canada.
Inward two and a half.
Currently fifth.
More faltering.
she came out all guns blazing first two rounds put herself in the business end of the field resting in fifth after the second round that will see her drop from the leaderboard not getting enough rotation ending up short of vertical as she goes in worth mentioning us watching the replays here the judges do not see the slo-mo's they do not see the replay they input their scores immediately as soon as a diver has hit the water the judges are required to put their scores in
And they're not allowed to look at each other's scores or ask each other or confer.
There's little dividers.
Can you see?
They're divided from each other.
It's like copying somebody else's homework, isn't it?
Not allowed to peek over and go, what did you think of that one?
6, 7, 5, 4, 6.5.
Annabel Smith has a back two and a half somersaults to perform now for us.
3.0 for the Australian.
That's better from Smith.
She was right down at the bottom of the leaderboard after a poor second round dive.
She will now pick herself back up with that one.
A back two and a half in the pike position.
As we look through the replay there, you can see the strain going through the body, pulling the top of the half of the body onto the bottom half to show the pike shape.
And then extend the dive to land on her head pretty much vertically.
Looks pretty much like she was doing this morning.
Not quite where she needs to be, not quite on form, just a little way off her favourite face and favourite place.
Now 2.8.
So we're down in the slightly lower tariff dives for the Malaysian.
That was her sabri.
She knows it's in the tuck position on the pike.
Back two and a half somersault with Tuck, so 2.8 on this.
Yeah, that's okay from Sabri.
As I mentioned, her first two opening round dives, a higher degree of difficulty, they're in the pike position.
Now, she struggles with this particular movement, the back, and the next one that she's doing is the reverse.
So she's opting for the easier degree of difficulty, the 2.8, the tuck position.
Spinning in a tuck position is easier than spinning in a pike position.
So Sabri landing okay on that one.
Is she, yeah, she's quite pleased, not sure.
Get a smile, a little inclination in the head, look back at the coach, what does the coach think?
The coach has never satisfied or something wrong, if you get a 10 or something wrong.
Alicia Black, a very decent start.
Let's see what she can carry on now.
Forward three and a half, although she's not being on top of her game, but let's see what the forward three and a half will bring for her.
Oh, lovely dive.
Yeah, so she isn't feeling top of her game, but that is around about the top of her game on this dive, even though she landed right on the corner of the board.
She waits, waits.
She's so, so strong.
Great dive from Alicia.
That will get over 70 points.
If it does, she'll go to the top of the leaderboard once again.
And that's where she was at the end of round one.
It won't be there at the end of round three, I don't think, but 71.3 puts her there temporarily.
14 points above Rebecca Gallantry.
But here is our current leader, Yang Yan Yi of Malaysia.
It's the back, two and a half, one more time.
And we'll see this from Hannah, not from Hannah Starling, but that's a chin.
Starling has something a little bit different to come up next.
But here is our current leader, needs 59 to retain that position.
Oh, faltering Yang Yi, over she goes.
Takeoff looked OK.
So generating enough spin speed, moving the arms, squeezing into the pike shape.
And then just reaching back a little bit too aggressively, tipping over.
That's going to get mid-range.
So maybe 5, 5.5 from the judges.
That will see her less than 50 points.
And yeah.
Just one dive like that can scupper your medal chances.
And although she's in second place right now, there are four more still to come in this round.
She might find herself in quite a plunge.
Hannah Starling.
Smile looks at the crowd, gets herself ready, focus on what she needs to do, have a little chat to herself, reverse two and a half somersaults with Pike for Hannah.
Nice, really nice, marvellous dive from Hannah, little bit of a skip on the takeoff, moving herself
towards the middle of the pool but she did have one of her feet over the end of the diving board which caused that.
She squares it up nicely she'll get sevens and that's a very good third round dive for the 19 year old from England.
Punching up they are in the positions just behind the medals and as we see some faltering here and it won't be in the top three at the end of this round but she's not too far away with our 63, three sevens
Esther Chin, 22 year old.
She's had a fair share of injury problems along the way.
I took a whole year out with ankle problems not so long ago.
New to America in 2009.
Silver in the University Games last year.
She is with a back two and a half somersaults.
Oh, that is the dive of her program so far.
We're looking for a vertical entry with no splash, and that is exactly what we got from Esther Chin on this dive.
We could see the first dive scoring above 8.5s.
That's straight up and down.
If the judges are awake and they're in a good mood, they might even go higher.
That's an 8.5 all the way for me.
And it is for the judges as well.
They have the same
view of that, as we do from the commentary box.
8.5 for Esther Chin.
And the Chinese-born Australian goes into the lead by 13 points from Alicia Black.
But the big movers and shakers are about to take to the board, though just coming out of medal position is Madison Keeney of Australia.
She wanted to do something about that, the 18-year-old.
It's the time she's had a little problem with this third dive.
Did she hit the diving board?
Now, as I'm watching it on the screen, I wasn't sure whether she's hit the diving board.
Let's have a look at the replay.
I think she does.
So she's that high.
She's right over the diving board.
Donk.
There you go.
She hits the feet on the diving board.
So the judges will quite clearly penalize that.
Now, that is a shame because she's so high.
It's good balance.
She just needed to move the dive a little bit further back.
She hits the feet on double.
Well, if it's deemed dangerous, judge number one thought, no, you hit the board.
I'm giving you 1.5.
The rest of the judges choosing fours and 4.5s.
That could be Madison Keeney out of the medals, and that would be a real shame.
Yeah, she's got a lot of talent.
Doesn't always put it all together at the right time.
This lady, however, is a complete reverse of that.
Forward two and a half, one twist.
Well, unfazed by the diver before her, hitting her feet on the diving board.
Jen is in the zone, focusing on what she can do, what she needs to do, one dive at a time.
That's how you win the Commonwealth Games.
And are we looking at the eventual champion?
Once again, one meter last night, midway through just over the three meter, and now clear in the top two with the Australian Esther Chin.
That's how it stands.
And Alicia Black has moved into the top three again.
She was one, slipped down a bit, but she's found her form in round three.
And she and Hannah Starling are in three and four.
Esther Chin, a great dive in round three.
It's put herself in position A. Rebecca Goundry on the front page.
So three English there.
Grace Reed's moved up to seven.
And it looks like a big, long haul back for Maddison Keeney and Annabel Smith.
if they're going to challenge for the medals.
Still mathematically possible because 1 to 11 separated by just 35 points.
I say just, it's quite a lot, but it's a massive difference between them.
Reverse two and a half for Chung.
Oh, yeah, Chung's definitely off again.
This was a real beauty in the prelim.
She got nines.
Well, I thought she should have got nines.
I think they gave her 8.5s.
One judge gave her a nine.
And she's done a lot of competing over these past few days.
This is day number four of the diving here.
Chung's been on pretty much every day.
She's starting to show fatigue.
You can see in her facial expression there that she's kind of toughing it out.
you worry about having the cameraman in your face because every diver when they come out the pool good manner and different has that camera right in their face do you not want to smack them at some point no I didn't even notice it he's focused on what you're doing Rebecca gallantry inward two and a half somersaults with tuck and this is down in the 2.7 range so consequently means this has to be very good if she's to retain her sixth position or push a bit further up the table around four for the
originally from Essex.
Oh what a shame she's opting for the easier inwards so in the tuck position you get less degree of difficulty just 2.7 and in the prelims it's really working for Becky here the takeoff is good the exit is okay and then she just lets it over rotate maybe needs to exit the dive a little bit sooner to ensure the vertical entry
She's watching the replay as you get the feedback from a coach, Aidy Hitchcliffe, saying good start, just needed to line up around the sides.
Sixes, yeah, less than 50 for her.
Now, Grace Reed's granddad did exhibition diving.
Her parents weren't involved in diving at all, but that's not Pamela Ware, by the way.
That is definitely Grace Reed on the board with a reverse two and a half somersaults with tuck.
Oh, lovely.
Well done, Grace.
I'm laughing because she's just raised her game.
So consistent.
She knows she's lacking in degree of difficulty, but she's matching.
Many of the athletes dive for dive with execution.
This will get her a handful of sevens.
She'll be, yeah, maybe close to 60 points with that.
Judge one, seeing as it's 7.5.
A couple of 7.5s discarded, as are a couple of 7s.
Look at that, 60.20, low tariff dive.
Very big dive in terms of execution.
And we're eighth place at the moment for the Canadian, but that's makeable in terms of bridging the gap.
Reverse two and a half again.
Yeah, that's going to help.
That's certainly going to help.
Fabulous dive off the back of a very average
Inward two and a half in the pike position.
This is the reverse two and a half.
She reaches back just allowing the dive to tip open.
Tip open.
Excuse me.
Tip over.
It's been a long day for me as well.
Very warm in this pool.
Stop making up words in a minute.
You never know.
Oh, you know we do that anyway.
Three sevens.
Sixty three.
Leon Taylor.
Giving you the full low down.
Full take on that.
And Grace Reed and Pamela were very close together now.
Two forty for the
Canadian 238 or Grace Reed, Annabelle Smith.
Forward three and a half somersaults with Pike, 3.1, the biggest dive.
Certainly is.
She needed a really good take off on that.
So in order to get the best take off, you need to land right on the end of the diving board.
She's just a little bit back from the end.
So has to squeeze into that Pike shake, duck her chin in as she enters the water in order to get to the close to vertical as possible, which she does a reasonable job on.
in mind where Anne Reid, she parks herself, which means in terms of medals, she's a long way shy of that.
Sabri, very, very good this morning.
I'd say she led at one stage, but she's at the other end of the pack this time.
Here comes her 2.8, different tariff on this.
Reverse two and a half somersaults.
Oh, she's nailed it.
Yes, much better.
Reverse two and a half in the tuck position.
It's only 2.8 degree of difficulty.
If you were to do it in the pike position, it's 3.0.
Sabri, the 15-year-old from Malaysia here, performing this dive to the very best of her ability.
I've been watching this in training.
It's one of her dives, a bogey dive potentially.
And that is very good.
8 and 7.5.
So the top three currently are separated by two points.
Pam where that was a separate and Grace Reed 240 plays 239 and 238.
Alicia Black is going to sell back in the third place.
Not feeling well at all.
First round dive and third round dive were exemplary.
How good would be to see her do a brilliant reverse two and a half somersaults with Pike in round four.
Well, it was almost brilliant, almost brilliant.
Beautiful takeoff.
Good distance from the diving board, squeezing into the pike shape.
Slight bend in her knees there.
The judges won't see that.
She just reaches back a little bit with a little bit too much effort, causing the dive to go over.
She'd done all the hard work and just faulted on the entry.
Good enough to put her in the lead for now.
2.8, 30, 54, but she'll be happy when this competition's over.
Let's get back in a bit, get some sleep.
Europeans are coming soon.
Couple of weeks time for her and some of the other British competitors here.
Eng Yan Yee of Malaysia.
Good place, so this reverse two and a half is good.
She could put pressure on the likes of Abel and Chin.
There's only one more round after this, so this has to be good.
Yes, that's good from Yang Yi.
Reverse two and a half in the pike position.
She faltered previously on the third round dive.
It's an okay takeoff.
She's a little bit scruffy into the pike shape.
She could get sevens on this.
That will hold her wherever she was at the end of last round, which I think was in fifth.
Putting pressure on the other athletes, making sure they have to hit their dives.
Alicia Black still in position A though.
So those things down with four to come in this round.
Black can't finish any worse than fifth.
And one place above that in fourth.
After round three was Hannah Starling.
Going for England.
19-year-old from Leeds, originally a swimmer.
Just before her ninth birthday to diving.
She's very glad she did.
Back two and a half somersaults with Pike.
3.0 for Hannah.
Yes, very nice.
Sneaks that dive in beautifully.
Little bit low on the water.
The takeoff is good, but she's not finishing the dive high enough in order to get the drop to get more than seven.
She does a very nice job of fitting that in.
So where will that put her?
I think close to Alicia's score.
so far.
She goes to number one only by Madame Marc at one point between her styling and Alicia Black in second but small returns to the face never far away from that face to be honest.
Here's our current leader Marjorie in front of Jennifer Abel.
Now can she put a bit of distance between herself and the Canadian with her reverse two and a half.
Oh, she was in the lead before, and now she is going to be difficult to beat.
The Australians cheering, and so they should.
Beautiful dive from Esther Chin.
Reverse two and a half in the pike position.
Drills that entry.
Could be 8.5s, maybe even a 9.
If it is, she's going to go 75.
And then she's going to be difficult to catch.
Just one dive to go for Esther Chin.
Two divers in this round.
76.50 for Esther Chen, 8.5 across the board.
So that's a big margin that she's opened up on the rest.
Nobody in the 280 range, everybody else in the 240s.
So Madison Keeney, I think that last dive has done for her chance of a medal.
It's a four with three and a half, 3.1.
Now you've got to give credit to this young lady.
She's only 18 and she is a super talent.
She has got so much potential.
Ruland's just on the end of the diving board, but look how high above the five meter board in the background she goes.
That's a beautiful dive.
68 points and that will squeeze the gap.
She'll only be 10 points off a medal now.
Is that too far?
Let's wait and see what happens.
It'll be down to the exciting last round.
Esther Chen goes to 284.
Where does Madison Keeney go?
239.2.
That is 10 points behind Hannah Starling.
9-9 Alicia Black.
So at the moment, Hannah Starling is in a medal position.
Jennifer Abel knows that she has to be at the top of her game now to catch Esther Chen with a forward three and a half.
Oh, well, she does need to be top of her game, and that is not top of her game.
She will go into the silver medal position at the moment with one round to go.
This is 3.1.
She would have needed eights to catch Esther Chin.
That is less than eights.
Just entering the water, still in a slight pike position.
Throwing up a bit of splash coming towards us.
She's going to have 11 points to make up in round number five if she wants to get the gold.
And she desperately does want to do the double here, does Jennifer.
But at the moment, she was silver medalist four years ago.
That's where she's heading in 2014.
Esther Chin, 284.
Look at that.
Anna Starling and Alicia Black battling it out for the bronze at the moment.
Heng Yan Ye in fifth and Pam Ware in sixth.
and then the rest with Grace Reed in there in ninth place.
So let's have a quick look at, before we go into the round, what the degree of difficulty is looking like for the English divers here.
Yeah, so Alicia Black is down on DD, 2.7, so it's going to be difficult for her.
Hannah Starling is the 3.0, Esther Chin 3.0, Madison Keeney 3.0, Jennifer April 3.0.
Game on.
Oh, it certainly is.
Chung Jun Hyeong on Malaysia, her last dive, 2.9 on this one.
No Chung very much off her game this evening.
What a shame because when she's diving well she's a delight to watch.
This evening tough day at the office finishing up here with a very average dive to go with a very average list of dives.
What a shame because she is a beautiful diver and we haven't seen the best of her this evening.
5.5s.
I suppose some people are making a night of it.
They've actually got the beers in and the drinks in and they're watching us tonight.
They've set their Saturday night aside for Leon and Bob.
He said having Leon on Saturday night on your telly out here.
It's like harking back to the winter.
Put the fire on.
Put your slippers on.
Rebecca Gallantry.
It's not going to be a medal day for her today.
In fact, she may well finish where she started in terms of the dive order in 11th place.
That's where she is right now.
Back two and a half somersaults with Pike for Becky to finish off with.
It's worth three point zero.
Oh, she sneaks out of it in nicely.
Just a little bit aggressive as she goes into the water.
The divers pretty much know when they hit the water whether it's good or not.
You get a feeling through your body, a bit of a shockwave maybe, and Becky would have felt the water hit her on her shins and ankles as she's gone in.
So she knows that she won't be coming up to eight, but she definitely knows it was better than four.
So sevens coming her way.
Sevens is exactly and precisely what she gets.
63 for Becky Gallantry, 292.20.
Grace Reed, last dive.
Biggest cheer of the night for her.
She has performed impeccably all the way through.
It's a low tariff dive to finish with, but it's the quality of the diving which has been so impressive from Grace.
As it was from James Heatley when he was diving in the men's event.
Back two and a half somersault with tuck for her.
Last dive for Scotland's Grace Reed.
She finishes off in style.
A little bit too much splash being thrown up.
She has done so well in the one meeting yesterday, prelims and finals, and today in the three-meter prelims and finals.
Her coach Jenny Lee Moon will be thrilled.
So will the crowd.
So will her parents, who are both here to watch her.
Great dive.
Good finish.
And what a wonderful Commonwealth Games.
Her second, would you believe, at the age of 18.
And nearly 300.
Nearly 300.
She would have loved to have been there.
Well, she's not too far shy.
And I'm sure the parents have got a picture of the scoreboard, which currently shows her in first place.
She's not going to finish there.
She's not going to finish in the medals.
But for the time being, she is heading the table.
And we're in sixth.
Forward two and a half.
Somersault's one twist.
3.0 for finishing off.
And she finishes off with a marvellous dive.
3.0, the forward 2.5-1 twist.
We're going to see this a lot.
Coming up, there's going to be the consecutive forward 2.5-1 twist.
Only two athletes coming up at the next eight electing not to do this.
Pamela's starting it off.
Good, 7.5s.
Yeah, nice.
67.50.
She is the first of the divers to go over 300.
308.10 would not, I don't think be enough.
So a quick calculation.
Hardly likely to be good enough for a medal today.
Rather disappointing at Annabel Smith today.
Just some quite worked out for her.
Either in the prelims or in the final tonight.
Forward two and a half with one twist as we mentioned.
She'll see a lot more to finish off.
It's a solid finish for Manuel Smith.
She was in 10th after the fourth round.
I think she'll be around about that place after that as well.
Even though that's a good dive, lots of the girls finishing on their best dives, which makes sense.
You want to finish on a good one.
This is good from Smith.
Probably identical scores coming her way as we saw for the Canadian Pamela just before her.
Seven point fives across the board, 67, so she doesn't quite get over the Rubicon of the 300.
Next up it is Davita Sabri.
We've seen a bit of a mixed bag from her today.
Very impressive in parts in the morning, not quite so this evening.
And again,
it's that forward two and a half so you're able to look and see what you think along with the judges 3.0 on the dd oh faltering on her last dive as well it's unfortunate because uh well for 15 she's doing a sterling job isn't she
Lots to learn.
Great Commonwealth Games.
Lots to take away, but no medals.
And she will drop down the leaderboard there.
Probably behind Rebecca Gallantry and Grace Reed.
At one stage, she was ahead of both.
45.
That's where she's gone on that.
Another great return.
And there are six more to go.
The one, two, three is Ware, Smith, and Reed.
But I don't think any of those are going to get medals now.
Alicia Black, still in fourth place and still in a position to challenge.
But, and here is the big but, it is a low tariff dive, 2.7.
It's a bit like Tonya Couch on the 10, finishing with a lower tariff dive, but one that she feels comfortable with.
And this is an inward two and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Well, she's giving it her best shot.
She isn't feeling very well this year.
Shaking her head as she comes up.
She knows as soon as you hit the water, you'll feel parts of your body going through.
And if it's smooth, it's a rip entry.
If you get hit by the water, which is what Alicia's happened, that means she's throwing up splash.
She won't get above sevens on this.
Low degree of difficulty.
She will not win a medal.
What a shame.
Hope she feels better soon.
Yeah, get well soon, Alicia.
She just wants to get away from here and get straight to bed.
Just recover, but good luck.
I know she's with the Europeans very shortly, so a couple of weeks to recover and get us back in full check again.
Heng Yang Yee of Malaysia, fifth place.
So still got a target of a top three finish.
One more time, the 3.0, forward two and a half for the next Malaysian.
Yeah, it's good.
You hear the Malaysian contingent shout and cheer.
There they are.
Yeah, they like it.
And she's done a very good job there.
Toes right over the end of the diving board.
She manages to pop the dive out.
That will put her top of the leaderboard, actually, with that.
We're still, four divers still to come.
Wow, it's going to be right down to the wire.
This is good stuff.
She's diving at its very best, nice and close.
We have no idea where the medals are going yet.
Nor does she, but she might have one with that.
308.20.
Out of the top she goes just, did you believe, 0.1 of a point ahead of Panware.
That's how close.
Super tight.
Alice Darling is in third place.
She does have a high tariff dive.
Alicia Black.
It is a forward two and a half somersaults, one twist.
You probably know that by now.
Come on, Hammer.
Third place, yeah?
See if she can do it.
Oh, it's a tremendous dive from Hannah Starling.
Will that be enough?
She's thrown down the gauntlet to the rest of them.
Let's wait and see what happens.
Wow.
I am super impressed.
Beautiful dive.
That's her dive of the competition.
That's going to get over 65 points, and that might be enough for a medal.
I'll put my rather damaged reputation on the line and say it will be good enough for a medal.
I'm sure, sure now with that.
She's got to put pressure on everybody else.
Got Esther Chin, the leader.
Jennifer Abel to come.
Masinkini in between.
Of course, Masinkini is still mathematically going to overtake that.
But at the moment, in number one position is Hannah Starling with 316.95.
Interesting stuff.
Now, 32 is all Esther Chin needs to overtake Hannah on her forward two and a half.
Well, I think we could be looking at the Commonwealth Games champion right there.
She had a bit of a lead.
Jennifer Abel probably is the only one that can catch her.
Esther Chin has been rocking it this evening, and that's a really good dive to finish, but it's not out of Jennifer Abel's reach.
It's not as good as Hannah Starling's it'll get me or mid-60s probably with sevens coming her way.
Yep, three four seven is the point to beat and only Abel could do that and she is up after Madison Keeney.
I think it's 75 although that's maybe 76 she needs so it's going to have to be a spot on that she can make it her last dive which is a different dive from everybody else's that you've seen recently.
Now Madison Keeney
cannot catch Esther Chin.
She can catch Hannah Starling with a 77.7 on this forward two and a half.
Anything under 77 Hannah has a medal.
Oh, it's a good dive from the Australian.
I do not think that will be good enough for her to stand on the podium.
Of course, she hit her feet on the diving board in dramatic fashion.
So that means that Hannah Starling will win at least the bronze.
At least the bronze.
That's good diving from the Australian.
She is a super talent.
But I am absolutely thrilled for Hannah Starling, who I can now confirm will stand on the podium.
She will at least on rung three.
because Esther Chin has a medal, Hannah Starling has a medal.
What color we will discover in the next minute.
The scenario is straightforward.
It's easy.
It's simple.
It's 73.5.
In other words, kind of eight and a halves really for Jennifer Abel for gold for Canada.
No, it won't be gold for Canada.
It's gold for Australia.
That will be, I think, good enough for silver.
She only needs fives, 5.5s to ensure the silver.
It's not very good.
It will be very close, but I think it's good enough.
It's a drop dive from the, well, not defending champion, but the one meter champion.
Silver medalist four years ago.
You can see her disappointment.
Silver again for Abel.
Gold for Australia, Esther Chin.
And another medal for Team Inga.
They're the Australians celebrating.
What a contest.
Great diving from Esther Chin.
Esther Chin taking the gold.
Jeff Abel with the silver.
But Hannah Starling,
who looked very good this morning, has improved to her standard, the 316.95 she got in the end.
Good enough for third place, edging out Madison Keeney, Eng and Pamela Ware, the bronze medalist from last year at the world championship.
So well done, Hannah Starling, a major step forward for the 19-year-old from Leeds.
But it's bronze for her, Canada with Jennifer Abel getting a silver to add to her gold in the one meter.
But Esther Chin looked very good in the one, looking good in three with the gold.
And there's the 7 to 12.
Alicia Black in 7, not feeling at all well.
We do wish her well because you imagine competing at this kind of level and not feeling at your best.
Annabelle Smith in eighth, Grace Reed finishing in ninth, Rebecca Gallantry in tenth.
We'll leave you with some images of that women's three meter springboard.
We're about half an hour away from the men's 10 meter platform.
You know what that means?
The arrival of Daly and of Matthew Mitchum as well.
Hope you'll join us for that.
I'm sure you will.
And we will be on BBC Three as well.
You want to watch it on the big telly.
7.30 BBC Three for the men's 10 meter platform.
Well done Hannah Starling.
Well that's Chin and Jennifer Abel as well with the gold and silver but nice bonus bronze if you like for Hannah Starling from Leon and myself back with you in about 25 minutes.
I'm so excited for the moment and I think we can start to prepare and we just want to get it out there.
Absolutely.
We're going to do that after the transition is done.
It's really great that you're doing what you're doing.
You're really doing what you are.
You're doing what you are.
Okay.
Ladies and gentlemen, the official results of the women's three-meter springboard final.
In first place, and the winner from Australia, Esther Chinn, 340.25.
Second place, silver medalist from Canada, Jennifer Amell, 324.7.
Third place, bronze medalist from England, Hannah Starling, 316.95.
In fifth place,
in sixth place from Canada, Paul O'Rourke, 308.12.
Seventh place from England, Lucille Lack, 300.95.
Eighth place from Australia, Emma Smith, 298.95.
Ninth place from Scotland, Grace Reed, 297.5.
Tenth place from England, Rebecca Gallagher, 292.2.
Eleventh place from Malaysia,
earned Betis 3, 284.2 and it's one place from Malaysia, child gentleman, 271.95.
Oh!
That's what you want.
divers, coaches and team managers.
Please be aware of the walls and our clothes.
We would appreciate your assistance in clearing the hall.
Then we'll have the small events, 10 metre platform final.
Please make their way to the front room and get ready for their parade.
Yeah.
Coming.
Hi.
I'm sorry.
Oh.
So ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gals, we are almost ready for our last diving competition, the men's 10-metre platform final.
In this competition, all dives will be performed from the very top board, the 10-metre.
Once again, we have seven judges sitting in the high chairs alongside the board.
The divers must choose six different dives.
One from forwards, one back, one reverse, one inward, one twist.
and one armstand.
The armstand group of boards is the only group that can be used on the platform.
They may use a forward or a backward armstand.
All six of the dives have no limits on the difficulty, so look out for 2.5, 3.5 and 4.5 subsets.
Once again, they've submitted their dive sheets in advance of the competition, and once submitted, they cannot now change those dives.
Oh, it's the money that you've been holding in.
Yeah, 20 minutes to come around the edge.
It's not a big city, it's South Africa.
This is my home after the determination of American runner.
I couldn't get the opportunity today.
So the race is lost on the bank.
The subject of the race is Shaquille O'Connor.
O'Connor is not here at the moment.
She's not at the moment.
She's not here at the moment.
I would like to thank you for taking the time to join us.
We did all ourselves.
We made the cabinets, we made the diamonds, we bought the wood, and we made the ones that the dogs died on.
And in the end, it was just the swap.
I spoke to a kind friend of mine who lived with me for a couple of days, and quite a lot of people told us that we were trying to make it work.
So, I messed up some of the previous things, so I thought, let's try this thing again, and I went to a certain specialization outside of the main building, and found out about the competition, and one of the things that I got out of it was that they were all doing it and competing, and it's too common now to be true.
It's very satisfying, very satisfying to see that everybody has got the courage to do what they want to do.
It's time, it's time for you, it's our time.
We're going in, we're going in, we're going in, we're going in, we're going in.
Yeah.
Ladies and gentlemen, we're nearly ready to begin.
Put our hands along to the track.
We are ready to count us down.
I'll make sure you and your friends are ready.
Are you ready?
Ten, nine,
Ladies and gentlemen, please make some noise and welcome the athletes for the men's 10m raffle final.
Representing India, Siddharth Banerjee.
Representing England, Matthew Dixon.
Representing Malaysia, Joe Huey.
Representing Australia, Dominic Bedcourt.
Representing New Zealand, Veng Yan Lee.
Representing England, James Denny.
Representing Malaysia, Oi Tze Liang.
Representing Canada, Visal Nguyen Dao.
Representing Canada, Maxime Bouchard.
Representing Australia, Matthew Mitchell.
Representing England, Tom Daly.
Please welcome the individuals for this session.
Referee Eric Brooker.
Assistant Referee Susan Lomba.
Judge 1, Mea Valence.
Judge 2, Shahrukh Khan.
Judge 3, Jane Ogden.
Judge 6, Jillian Rooker.
And Judge 7, Marco Valerian Palazzo.
with the referee's permission.
We have our first diver on the board, representing India, Siddharth Pardeshi.
First diver in six rounds of the 10 meter platform for men will be the Indian Siddharth Pardeshi.
It's a forward three and a half somersault with Pike he's going to go for.
Leon and I both watched quite closely his preparation for tonight's
final.
Little bit concerned for this young man, to be honest, he wasn't really getting many of his dives right.
Hopefully that's all stored away.
Here's his first round dive.
Well, surfboard moment to kick this final off.
Big tidal wave being thrown up there by the young Indian, only 17 years old.
And this is pretty reflective of what he was doing in training.
Over he goes.
Get your surfboards out.
Surf is up for sure.
Oof.
Over he goes.
I cannot say I'm terribly surprised by that.
Threes and 2.5s.
Watching his build up to this.
I think I saw maybe one diver looked OK.
He's putting his body through quite a testing and troubling build up.
Now 14 year old Matthew Dixon from Plymouth.
Great to have him here.
And great to see what he can do on this forward three and a half somersaults with Pike.
3.0 for the young man.
His best marks, by the way, 398.25.
Oh, he's a little bit short of vertical, but he does get that rip entry.
Bit of a crowd favourite here, and I'm not surprised.
Just tiny, his head is only just above the bars, the safety bars up on the 10 metre.
As you see clearly, as you see on the replay, the judges of course do not see the replay.
He enters the water short of vertical, so the marks will reflect that.
49.5 for Matt.
Whereas it was 60 this morning, so he's 11 points down on how he started in the prelims.
Chu Yue has, like some of the other Malaysian divers, actually been a bit of a mixed bag this week.
He's really on it.
He's really on it and gets big marks.
He too starts with a forward three and a half somersaults with Pike, 3.0.
A couple of other divers will do this one too.
Nice from Chu Yue, looking for that vertical entry, splashless, and he gets exactly that.
He's a little bit ragged.
Mind you, he gets into that pike shape eventually, but his form is good.
He's going to get eights on that, which is excellent.
I've been watching him on his other dives, and he tends to be a little bit here and there, but that's a solid start.
72 for Chu Yue.
One of two Malaysians in the final.
Coach is saying where that can improve.
Perhaps we can improve for the remaining five rounds as well.
Now this man started like a train this morning.
His opening dive, the armstand back double somersault to an arm twist we're about to see.
Looked very, very impressive.
See what we can do with this one.
Oh, it's nearly as good as the prelim.
That's a huge dive to open with.
He got massive 91 on this in the prelim.
He isn't going to be far away from that now.
This will get mid-80s somewhere.
It's 3.6 degree of difficulty.
He's going to get eights.
A little bit too much splash being thrown up for nines.
Dominic Bedgood opens his campaign with a very good dive.
86.4 for Dominic Bedgood.
14 points clear to UE.
And that takes him with 49.5 in third place currently.
So he does, Helen.
Looking forward to two more English divers to come.
James Denny up in a couple.
And Tom Daley, because he was the best qualifier this morning, will go last.
So here's Li Fengyang, now of New Zealand, formerly of China, forward three and a half.
Oh, just letting the dive run away.
The takeoff was good.
Probably a little bit too much forward momentum, so he moves away from the diving board quite considerably.
This can make controlling the dive a little bit more challenging.
He comes out with plenty of time just rolling over there.
A little bit of splash being thrown up.
So 3.0, relatively low degree of difficulty compared to some of the dives in his repertoire.
And he's a little bit off the pace.
58.5.
Sticks him in behind Bedgood.
Once again, a strong opening for the Australian, who you saw as we were joining.
Chuyue in second place.
Now James Denny, second of the Englishman.
Ninth of the Europeans on the 10-meter board.
Got over 400 points with it.
That is the silver medalist on the platform at the British Championships earlier this year.
And he will start with a 3.2.
Nice opening gambit for James.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck for the second of three Englishmen and you know who comes third.
Oh, there's a good start from James Denny, really clean on the water, just a little bit short as he goes in.
In fact, he doesn't quite straighten out enough.
Take off his good, squeezing into that tuck shake.
Three and a half somersaults.
Pikes out, has a good look at the water, but you see that he's got his backside sticking out as he goes in.
He won't get more than sevens for that, which is a shame, because if he'd have straightened out completely, he'd have been getting eights, maybe even more.
Seven, seven, seven.
On a 3.2 DD, we have DDD here.
Denny, Daly and Dixon.
Utin Yang of Malaysia.
Already showing what he can do on the three metre board by going on to win it.
And absolutely a few English hearts, not least of all, Jack Law.
Going from three to ten.
I haven't quite put in the performance yet to suggest he's a medalist, but it's the final now, not the prelims.
This is where it really matters.
Back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists in the pike position, 3.2.
Yeah, dive very well this morning.
Utsi Liang made one mistake, which is why he's middle of the pack.
Divers dive in reverse order from the standings in the prelim.
This is good for Utsi Liang, 3.2.
It's actually a relatively easy twist in comparison to what you're going to see Mitchum, Daley and Denny try.
The back two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists.
This is the two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
It's worked out okay for Ooh.
The marks we wait for.
The judge is either indecisive or the technology is letting us down at the moment, so we can't bring you what he's got as yet.
It will be appearing on your screen.
Oh no, we have a judge who's not pushed their button properly.
So they have to re-input it before we can bring you all the scores.
Remember, only the middle three will count towards the total, 7.5s and 8s.
Did have a question about why all the marks are not counted.
It's about finding the average.
So the two highest and two lowest are discounted to get the average scores.
Otherwise the subjectivity plays too much of a part if all the marks count.
So seven judges, two highs, two lows removed and three count multiplied by the degree of difficulty gives you total for the dive.
Easy as that.
Straightforward.
Much more straightforward than doing the dives.
Forward three and a half somersaults with Mike for Ruriendo.
I was very impressed with Vincent Riando and next up Max Bouchard, both of these young Canadians.
Vincent is certainly young, 17 years old.
He's got a bright future in front of him.
This is his easiest eye, 3.0.
He certainly starts his campaign off in pretty steady style.
need six dives six consistently good dives to be anywhere near the medals let's see how this young man gets on well if we presume it will be daily at mitcham going head to head somebody needs to claim the bronze could easily be vincent riendo let's uh just come out of world juniors maybe his 10th in australia
Maxime Bouchard retired after 2008 World Juniors in Germany.
Didn't think he could cut the mustard, but it's been persuaded to come back.
He's kind of held together with sticky tape.
There's a lot of metal in that body.
Arm stand back, triple somersault with tuck.
3.3, there'll be different variances of the arm stand, we'll see.
Some people like to do it with a towel.
Some people do not.
Maxime is one of those.
Oh.
Well, my ooh was because he wasn't meant to do that.
Had a little bit of a wobble in the arm stand balance there.
Lost his balance, manages to hold himself, but then when he goes eventually,
His takeoff isn't quite as strong as it normally is, and so as he exits the dive, he thinks he's lower to the water, arches through to try and pull it in, but it's an error, and he over-rotates.
It's not disastrous, but it wasn't as strong as I've seen in training from Maxim.
In an event and a competition of this quality, anything below sevens is not going to help your medal prospects.
6.5 just puts him a little bit behind the pace in round one, about behind.
Bedgood, Buzi Liang, Chu Yue, Vincent Riando and James Denny.
Only ahead for the moment of Lee Dixon.
Not Lee Dixon obviously, Lee and Dixon.
I don't think he's diving yet.
It's a new pairing of Gary Lilica and Lee Dixon on the board.
Now a little chat with the Canadian coach about something there, Leon.
Yeah, let's wait and see.
I don't have any microphones down there.
That was the referee.
There was a discussion.
I have no idea what was discussed.
If you are going to make a protest, you need to make a protest straight away that maybe the referee turned it down.
We'll find out afterwards.
So there's a little disruption.
Now the competition really starts.
The head-to-head.
Mitchum versus Daly, take two.
Four years ago, it was Daly.
Who will it be this evening?
Well, I'll try and do, if I remember, is give you their marks this morning so you can compare how they've done tonight.
81 on the forward three and a half somersaults for Matt Mitchum this morning.
Oh, there you go.
The pressure beginning to tell.
Did the delay cause him to lose concentration?
Because that is an error for Mitchum.
His easiest dive and he's fluffed it.
Their door is wide open.
You cannot start your campaign with like a 60-pointer, not when you're taking on Tom Daley.
What are we going to see this evening?
6.5s is what you see there.
And that is some 23 points down on what he did this morning.
So already a big amount of ground to make up for the gold medalist from Beijing 2008, silver medalist four years ago in Delhi.
And the winner on the synchro last night with Dominic Bedgood.
So Tom Daly, arm stand to start.
Slightly different version of it from what we've seen thus far.
Arm stand back triple somersault.
Now when he performed this dive in the preliminaries this morning, 73.50.
Just to give you a little heads up, the dive he has a problem with is coming next.
73.5 though on his arm stand back triple this morning.
Hello Tom Daley!
Welcome to the men's 10 meter platform final.
This is the defending champion.
That is his first dive and he's gonna get nines and maybe even some tens.
He has capitalized on Mitchum leaving the door open.
Tom Daley has absolutely smashed it.
90 points plus.
Beautiful dive.
Game on.
Should we just stop the competition there?
94.5 compared to 73.5.
What a massive swing.
23 points down, Mitcham.
21 points up, Daly.
Swing of 44 points on one dive from this morning to evening.
And there it is.
You don't even see.
Matthew Mitchell in the frame there.
He's on page two.
That's good.
Starting well again for Australia.
We're having problems with a photography problem that we had in London.
Everyone wants to get a snapshot of Tom Daly.
We know how it affected his diving in London.
So the crowd just being told to turn those flashes off.
Tom Daly has a lead of eight points already and maybe more importantly has a lead of some 36 over Matt Mitchell after round one.
Now we're a little bit concerned for this young man because we saw him in practice tonight in training and warm up and he wasn't getting anything right.
Let's hope he gets through his six unscathed.
Inward three and a half somersaults with tuck for Siddharth Bhadeshi.
This is his big dive of the program at three point two.
Well, Siddhartha was, well, he was almost there.
All the components were in the right place.
His takeoff is good enough.
Good jump, good extension from the legs, moving a safe distance from the diving board.
Spots the water, just isn't quite confident enough to straighten out quick enough.
He still hits the water a little bit loose, a little bit soft, and therefore won't get more than the marks coming up.
Fives, 5.5s is about right.
If he was a bit more confident on the exit of the dive, he could even get 7s.
I'll be interested to see what he does in the remaining dives because what he was doing this morning taking about 25-30 seconds over each dive and it seemed to be counterproductive as he was trying to get himself prepared for it.
It seemed to be too much thinking and execution of the dives was suffering because of it.
14 year old Matt Dixon, one of the European juniors now stepping up to the senior ranks with a reverse two and a half somersaults with tuck only 2.8 degree of difficulty so
keeping up with the others.
This needs to be very good for the young man.
Oh, it's a tremendous entry into the water.
He's just a little bit untidy.
As he gets in, I'll tell you through it on the replay.
The jump is good.
He's only tiny, is he?
14 years old.
Spots the water, kicks out, looks over his toes, reaches back, just tipped his feet over with him.
So he got eight and a halfs on this earlier.
I think this will only get seven and a halfs.
But he's loving his final.
He did a little bit of a wiggle and a wobble on the way in.
So, yeah, 7.5s.
All right.
Middle of the pack in terms of marks.
The strength on the board is not a question.
The strength in terms of getting the door open to go to the cool down area might be.
Chuyue.
Here comes another arm stance.
Different to the one we saw from Tom Daly.
This one has a double somersault and one and a half twists attached to it.
We'll see this dive done by Utse Liang and by Rien Do and also by Mitcham in this round.
3.2 degree of difficulty.
Chiu Yue after round one is in fourth place.
Nice from Chiu Yue.
Sometimes struggles with his form.
The form on this dive is good.
You're looking for legs straight, toes pointed, aesthetically pleasing movements, i.e.
look pretty, impress the judges.
His pike shape isn't quite as deep as it needs to be, so he's swinging around, looking a little bit out of control as he squares up.
So the judges
Yeah, I'm not sure which way they're going to go with them.
Well, a couple, well, six to seven and a half, so they weren't sure either.
No, they weren't.
A complete mixed bag of scores.
Luckily, it's going to match what you were saying earlier on.
We do discount the top ones and the bottom ones.
Just the middle three will be included in that score.
And for the time being, at least, with still plenty to go.
He's leading at 139.
That will not last for long.
Probably be overtaken on this dive, although after a great start this morning, Dominic Bedgood had problems with this.
His second after round one is his inward three and a half somersaults, 3.2 for the first of the Australians.
We'll see Mitchum being the other.
Yeah, it wasn't very good this morning.
That is better.
It can still be improved.
He does all the hard work.
The takeoff is very, very strong.
Squeezing into the tuck shape, completes the dive very easily.
Just doesn't quite straighten his body out on the end.
If he straightens out, he couldn't even get as high as nines.
Because he's going in slightly rounded, shall we say.
He's only going to get that 7.5.
Cole Minnis with Matt Mitchum last night in the 10 meter synchro.
Looking to try and add to his collection.
not probably the moment on that form going to be in the top three shakeup but there's such big tariffs attached to the dives that come later we're talking about three point sixes a lot of them three point sevens three men doing the forward four and a half which is three point sevens is a minuscule in comparison three point two for lee fen yang of new zealand inward three and a half one more time in the tuck position
Yep, he makes that dive so easily.
3.2 is still very, very challenging.
Lots can go wrong.
You've got to jump away from the diving board.
He is a safe distance.
Yeah, hikes out of that very early, but then feels as though he's stuck.
And so ducks his chin in and just rolls over.
So he won't be getting eights.
He'll be getting sevens.
67.277 to add towards our total if you are new to all this.
And I know those of you who have been with us all week probably think, well, we know this by now, but it is the degree of difficulty multiplied by the scores that count to add up to that total score.
We've seen Tom Daly do it, and we'll see James Denny do it now.
The arm stand back triple somersault, opening 67.20 for James Denny.
Silver medal in the platformer synchro last night.
His role model is Jensen Button.
No pit stop here for James Denny.
Yeah, it's good.
It's good all the way until the entry.
So James, steady balance, strong push off the hands, flicking the legs, squeezing into the tuck shape.
And just here as he goes into the water, just allowing his feet to tip over with him, giving the impression the dive is going over, but really just needed to extend a little bit more, point his toes back towards the diving board to stay vertical.
Minor error.
Yeah.
Just communicates with the coach, Adi Hitchcliffe there from the Leeds Diving Club.
Six point fives to that total of sixty four point three five.
But good ahead of him.
Chu Yue ahead of him.
Manu will have his eye on at least a bronze medal and he won't be seeing Daley and Mitcham as invincible.
Here's Utsay Liang of Malaysia.
That's the arm stand time.
Regulars will know I just as little bit on the arm stand divers think it's nothing to speak of.
I'd say most mere mortals do find it quite a tricky thing to watch.
Arm stand back, double sub-assault, one and a half twists in a free position.
Third after round one.
leaving the dive marginally short of vertical there as he enters the water.
Steady arm balance is great, isn't it, when you get the camera to zoom in just to see the concentration and the effort that goes into these dives.
The judges, of course, do not see the replay.
Their marks are already in the computer.
Ouziliang, short of vertical, only going to get six and a halfs.
Wow.
Will that be good enough to stay in contention of the medals?
Let's wait and see.
Not likely with Mitchum and Davy still to come.
And indeed Riyadou had a very good start.
So although he's third right now, that could easily be sixth or possibly seventh at the end of this round.
There will be a lot of fluctuations in position.
But this young man, a very, very impressive start.
He is definitely
future star of Canadian diving.
There's no Ryany McCormick now.
He's retired from 10 meter, come down to three and one.
So they're looking for a new star.
Let's see how that's Departee in the past on the 10 and three.
Perhaps here's his heir apparent Vincent Riendol.
Arms down back, double somersault, one and a half twists in the free position.
Off he goes and down he goes.
That's really, really tidy.
Good.
Strong.
Push off the hands.
Pops up into the air.
That's really tight.
His feet actually come quite close underneath the tower.
He needs to be careful of that.
He does lose his feet.
Helicopter feet marginally.
So his feet kind of flutter.
So the judges might, if they spot that, penalize.
One judge has.
Judge number three giving him a six.
The other's ignoring or missing.
The feet flutter.
I like a feet flutter.
But I never win.
7.5s look out towards the total.
Maxime Bouchard.
He's happy to be with us after the problems he's been through.
Forward three and a half somersault with Pike for the Canadian.
Yes, nice tidy straight up and down.
Clean vertical entry into the water.
3.0 degree of difficulty.
So you know what, if he does well, he's going to be in the mix for the bronze and he's diving very well.
That's going to nudge over 70 points, which is great because it's only 3.0 degree of difficulty.
eights across the board.
You'll see an 8.5 there but discard that and because it is discarded only three marks the ones without the lights through them will add up.
Okay I did say I'd try and tell you what the main two divers got this morning.
Well this was a 75.6
But Matthew Mitchum, but as we mentioned, it's been a 23 points swing against him.
And Tom Daly got 21 more points on his opening dive than he did this morning.
So a big margin to make up already for Mitchum on his arm stand back double somersault two and a half twists.
Ninety nine will take him into the lead.
Not likely.
Or is it?
It's a beautiful arm balance.
He has cranked the start a little bit too much.
He gave it too much means and could not stop that rotation.
It's a tricky dive to do.
I've done it many times.
It's just a real pain because you've got so many twists to do to get in with the rotation.
It's very easy to over-rotate.
That's exactly what Mitchum's done.
He is lagging behind.
Now, this could prove to be critical.
Dropped another 12 from this morning.
Daly's next dive.
is crucial.
We've used a description before a few times and he would describe it too as his bogey dive.
Here's the description of it.
Back two and a half semisaults, two and a half twists in the pike position.
It's worth 3.6 degree of difficulty.
He was down in 37s this morning, 37.8.
That's why it was a huge swing to Mitcham in the election terms.
Now, he's composed himself.
Could take a long time over this.
Just look at the mannerisms and the facial expressions on this one.
Oh, it's better than this morning.
It's better than this morning.
He's still struggled with it.
That is a step in the right direction.
It's a step in the right direction, but it's not as good as he did in Mexico.
He's not extending his legs out the diving board.
The judges are going to give him sixes.
because he just, he needs an 11 meter platform.
If you're gonna take off like that, he just needs to extend the legs.
But the problem is at the start, he's not quite as relaxed as he needs to be.
He's watching the replay there.
The judges don't see the replay.
64.
Right, well, that's out of the way now, Tom.
Four more dives.
If you want the gold, it's yours to take.
And even though it wasn't up to spec and up to scratch for Daley, it's still a massive swing to him from Matt Mitchum again.
37 this morning, 64 in the evening.
Daley leads from Bedgood and Chuyue.
There are one, two, three moments.
James Denny on the second page, as is Matthew Dixon in 10, and Siddharth Bhadeshu is next in 11.
Now I'm going to put the clock on him here because he takes longer over this dive than does Rafa Nadal over a serve.
Something like half a minute this morning.
So he's ready to go.
Stopwatch on.
Well, according to my timekeeper, 28 seconds thinking about it, but only 1.5 seconds to complete the dive or 1.8.
So back two and a half in the pike position.
This is actually very good for the sit up in training.
He was every which way for upright and in the time when it counts in the competition, he's nailed it.
The man from India lands upright, vertical and good second round dive.
Well,
morning it didn't work for him the length of time he was cogitating but that worked all right and whilst he's not going to be in the top 10 the way things are looking he'll just try and get as many marks as he can huge cheer for the young man who really does seem to be relishing a chance of performing in front of this audience and the huge audience at home 14 years of age from Plymouth
bronze at the European Juniors and the British Championships a year.
It's very close to 400 marks.
Forward gymnast, now diver.
Matt Dixon, armstand forward, double somersault, one twist, 3.1.
Already you can see the strappy on his arm.
It's the battering the arm is taking.
Oh, it's a great takeoff.
It's so composed, so balanced.
Beautiful handstand.
You can see his gymnastics background here.
This is almost like a vault.
You're a gymnast at home.
You'll notice what needs to go in to get that forward rotation from a handstand without having a springboard and a vault to get off.
Just faltering on the entry into the water.
Cranks it a little bit too much and over he goes.
And for the time being into the lead he goes, but
As he's only the second one up, that's not going to last for very long, but 51.15, brilliant, immense, and completely unrepeatable in terms of his age experience for the young man from Leeds.
Now Chu Yue of Malaysia, third place at the moment.
Nice and solid opening couple of round dives.
This one will be performed in the tuck position, 3.3 degree of difficulty.
We will get up into the 3.6s very shortly.
And the 3.7s, Mitchum finishes with two 3.6s.
Tom Daley has that forward four and a half worth 3.7.
But this is a back three and a half somersaults for Chu Yue.
Oh, what a mess.
What a shame.
Foltering as he went into the water.
Drifting too far away from the diving board, which means that when you come out of the dive, it's difficult to control.
And over he goes.
That's our second or third surfboard moment of this competition.
Tidal wave incoming.
There we go.
Splash moving away from the diving board.
Judge three with Simon Cowell.
judge too well sorry in a completely different way Dominic Bedgood loves to repeat that six times because that's been spot-on for him so far today this is kind of where his program just unfolded a little bit in the prelims Dominic Bedgood currently
In second place, though.
Back three and a half somersaults with Tuck, the man who's at the moment putting the pressure on Tom Daley.
Well, that is exactly the same as Chuyui.
He went surfing on the bottom.
Way over.
Just showing how difficult these dives are.
And this is the time you need to get your surfboards out.
There's the wave.
I would expect good give us a wave.
They just did.
Threes 3.5s and well he was looking at medals just now.
He's going to have a big reparation job to do after that.
33 marks total.
That's going to slip him well down the Becky odd here.
1234567 more to go.
Could easily go from second down into seventh place here, possibly eighth.
Lee Fen Yang of New Zealand 3.3.
We'll see next three divers all do this in slightly different varieties.
The next two divers do it in slightly different varieties of this.
Back three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Next diver James Denny will do it in the pike position.
Oh, that's good from Lee.
That's how you do it.
So Chuyue and Dominique Bedgood went surfing.
And Lee has disappeared with that rip entry.
Just got his boots on there.
His feet are flat.
And then eventually points his toes.
Good entry to the water.
Marginally short vertical, but much, much better.
It's the best of the back three and a halfs in the tuck position.
And we've just seen three in a row.
Even at this stage, the minor medals are definitely up for grabs.
Tom Daly needs to keep the consistency going for the gold, because he's going to be untouchable if he does.
But silver and bronze, not out of the range of anybody in the top order at the moment, including this young man, James Denny.
We'll go with the same dive we've seen, but in a slightly different form.
Goes from tuck to pike.
next time by the way there's one that i've seen on youtube with no splash but uh it's gonna be very hard for this to be uh splashless mac three and a half pike big tariff 3.6 for james denny
Well, that's what him and Tom, one of the dives they used last night in the synchro.
And James doing the opposite to what he did in the synchro.
In the synchro, he went over, over a vertical.
Here he is slightly short.
In fact, he is quite short.
Who am I trying to kid?
He's landing pretty much on the backs of his legs, going loose in the lower back.
It is such a difficult dive.
And when it goes wrong, it can go drastically wrong.
He will drop down the leaderboard with that one.
Well, apart from Lee, everybody else is having problems with that dive in different configurations.
Including James Denny.
He's at 48.6 and more and more it's looking like there's not going to be as much pressure as we thought on Tom Daley.
I would say Liang was there or there about, but he had a four second Ryan dive.
So he needs to get it back on track with a fourth, three and a half with Pike.
That is back on track.
It's very good for Moutilier.
His easiest dive, 3.0.
Forward, three and a half in the pike position.
Such a strong athlete.
Leaps off the diving board.
Just rolling into the water.
He's going to get eights on that.
That'll help him.
Will he see himself top of the leaderboard?
Yes.
For the time being, he will.
First to go over the 200 mark.
208, to be precise.
Nine clear of Lee and 17 ahead of Bedcourt.
The main movers and shakers are about to perform.
At the halfway stage approaching.
Future of Canadian male 10 meter diving has arrived in Edinburgh.
Let's see whether he accepts that tag gratefully and gladly on this reverse.
Three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4 attached to this.
Oh, he's taking it on.
Yeah, the Canadians, both of them, both Vincent and Maxime to follow shortly.
Wow, good dives.
This one in particular, 3.4.
It's tricky.
Get it all the way around.
Anything above 70 points is good.
75 points, even better.
Then up into the higher echelons we go.
I would not be at all surprised if this young man isn't on the podium later on today.
Started with great confidence, started with a great smile, started with a great attitude.
It might well be a battle between the Canadians for medals here.
Or is it not going to be Matt Mitchum's night?
Perhaps two of them could sneak on to the medal podium.
Simon Bouchard is not too far shy of a top three place, in fact, with everybody else faltering.
Time for him to step up on that 3.4.
So we have some big tariff dives to come.
They get more immense as the competition goes on.
This is mid-range, really.
Not for Bouchard, though.
Reverse three and a half somersaults with Tuck for the second of the Canadians.
Oh, it's an unusual technique.
He's balancing on his tiptoes, but he's standing forwards.
That's highly unusual.
He took ages to go as well.
It's exactly the same dive as his teammate Vincent has just performed, and it's not as good.
So that means that Max will drop a little bit further away from where he was on the previous round.
He only needed seven and a halfs and eights, but that's only going to get 5.5s.
24 points behind his teammate now.
Three rounds ago, that can be made up.
But Liandau is setting the pace amongst the... Well, it looked like being the lesser medalist now.
Round three this morning was a very good dive for Matt Mitchum on his reverse three and a half.
That's his best dive of the competition.
88.4 he got, but he's down on his first two dives tonight.
Oh, it's a good dive for Mitchen.
He manages to keep the splash down.
It is the rip entry that we're looking for.
He does wash over a vertical.
So he's only going to get, well, eight and a halfs maybe.
He needed to be completely bolt upright to get nine and a halfs and tens, which is pretty much what he would need to put pressure on Tom Daley.
This is a big, big dive though.
85 points plus.
Well, he got 450 total this morning.
He's happy.
A little jig of joy and delight for Matt Mitchum.
Well, he's come close to emulating what he did this morning.
Still hasn't quite done it.
In terms of tariff, the weakest dive for Tom Daley.
Doesn't always translate into execution.
It will be though.
Any moment now, an inward three and a half somersaults with tuck for Daley.
takeoff is electric he's been working so hard on this boom on the start really good strong start just rolling over as he goes into the water he's going to get eight and a half's probably not good enough for a nine
Good enough, though.
He'll be over 80 points.
81.6, and he knows in his head how that compares with this morning.
Not that favorably.
81.6, but 83 points this morning.
So first time on his evening performance.
He's down on marks, but it's only marginal.
Tom Daly, Vincent Riendoe.
Mitchum has woken up and come to the party now in third place.
It would say Liang in fourth and the two other Englishmen in the field, James Denny in eighth and Matt Dixon in tenth.
So we've reached halfway.
It's looking good for Tom Daly with a 26 point gap between him and the rest right now.
But we are only halfway.
As I mentioned, the big dives, not for the likes of Siddharth Padeshi, but the main divers still to come.
OK.
28 seconds last time.
How long will you take over this one?
Reverse two and a half somersaults with Pike.
Still not quite ready to go.
So your TV hasn't frozen.
This is actually happening.
Well, next to me in the radio section, Karen Pickering has summed it up perfectly.
She shifted back in a chair and held herself because it doesn't tickle hitting the water at over 35 miles an hour.
And when you don't get anywhere near up by, that really does hurt.
You can tell why Siddhartha was taking his time and having to think about it.
It's a tricky dive.
Reverse two and a half in the pike position.
And he's just had the rough of the water.
This man made a steal or what?
He was doing something similar in the build-up and the training before the event itself and just took the knocks, got back on that 10-meter board, did it all over again, but no improvement from the practice, I'm afraid.
Matt Dixon is not too put off by that.
3.2 for the youngster.
He has senior debut at the Commonwealth Games, in with three and a half somersaults, 3.2.
He's probably safe from finishing bottom.
Let's see if he can make a few strides up with this.
What a dive from the 14-year-old from Plymouth.
He's absolutely smashed it.
Wow.
That is what he's capable of.
They've got some big scores coming his way.
I am liking that.
Good work, Matty Dixon.
Well, physically, he might look out of place here, but those marks aren't.
8.5, 8.5, 8.5, 81.6.
My oh my.
I did say he's not going to finish bottom.
He may well be a couple of places above that.
The performances of that kind.
That is sensational from the young man.
Just shows the promise he has down in Plymouth.
Andy Banks working so hard with him and the others.
Great little program.
Andy, of course, worked for 12 years with Tom Daly before he moved to London.
That's what special coaches do.
Chu Yue in with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, three point two for the Malaysian.
Wrong end of the field in ninth at the moment.
Oh, it's better from Chu Yue.
Yeah, his third round dive, the back three and a half when he went surfing cost him his spot on the leaderboard.
This is better.
Not as good as Matty Dixon, but not far off.
Strong takeoff.
She used to use a towel, that's a comfort thing.
It's a non-slip surface on the platform and some divers prefer the grip of a towel, which is the blue towel that you saw on the 10 meter there, just as Chiu Yue was performing his dive.
76.80.
Doesn't look to me like he's going to be pushing for a medal.
Stay with big tariff times, which can easily be dropped or failed on occasion.
Can't always make that prediction even at this stage, but two rounds to go.
Looks like he's not going to be in the shakeup.
This man still could be a bit in and out.
Great start in both the prelims and the final for Dominic Hedgood.
3.4.
Reverse three and a half.
60 will put him above Chuyui.
He'll be looking, though, for 80s if he can.
Well, it's better from Bedgood.
Better from Bedgood.
This went to Rai in the prelims.
He almost gets it right here in the final.
He just needs to look back a little bit more.
Marginally short vertical as he goes in.
It's still a good dive.
way over 70 points.
Where will that put him?
76.5 is what he gets in terms of total marks and for the time being he keeps changing hands as it always does at this stage as divers just get their noses in front of the opposition but we're not down to the sharp end by any means yet.
Seven divers to go and
Both Lee and James Denny will be performing that dive.
Reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.4.
Lee looking to go crashing through the 200 barrier here, currently in fifth place.
So again, not too far shy of a top three place.
Yes, he is.
It just goes to show how difficult these dives are.
This one in particular, the reverse three and a half.
He's got to jump away from the diving board, spin backwards towards it, which is exactly what Lee does.
He's just squeezing his shape in there, comes out if he's diving a little bit too early, lands flat on his back.
What a shame.
Yeah, it looks like his chance of a medal, which looked very good before that dive.
have just evaporated at the Royal Commonwealth call in Edinburgh.
Former Chinese diver, retired, came back coaching in Wellington.
I think he is still coaching as well as well as performing, but the person who decided retirement was not for him.
Consideration retirement for this man, 20 years of age.
Of course, Tom Day's been around a long time, so they're both about the same age.
We haven't seen anywhere near as much of
James Denny with the synchro with Tom Daley last night.
Here he is on the individual with the reverse three and a half the tuck.
You saw how it went last time.
Let's see how it goes this time.
Can he improve on what we've just seen from Li Fenyang?
Oh, yes he can.
That's much better.
James jumps quite far from the diving board on this.
I know he'll be working hard with AD up in Leeds High Performance Diving Center on this.
Doesn't really need to be that far away from the diving board.
Makes it tricky to control, but he does a good job on that.
So just throwing up too much splash as he goes in.
That's much better than this morning and better than the Synchro competition last night.
progress and that's what they're looking for still not quite where his coach would like it to be or indeed where he wants it to be but six point fives in seven means that he's above a few doing Fenyang Li now and three points clear of Matt Dixon who would say Liang with some time is faltering at the moment and not quite getting their top scores
He's in range on a medal, already got the three meter.
And as he does go through the card, one meter, three meter, and 10 meter.
And here's back three and a half.
Send him towards 300 points if he gets it right.
Oh, and he does.
I thought he was out way too early on that.
But he knows exactly where he is.
Good aerial awareness.
Do you know where you are when you're spinning around and falling down towards the earth at breakneck speed?
No.
Yes, is the answer from Ootsi Liang.
That's good.
He was a little bit early, but manages to pull it round.
Looking back up to the hole that he just created as he punched through the water with his hands in a grab position.
Getting feedback from his coach himself, an exceptional diver in his day.
Used to dive against me.
He's a bit slimmer then, though.
Not as handsome, obviously.
On to Vincent Riendoe.
3.2 degree of difficulty.
This young Canadian, 17 years of age, back at what he's done so far.
Diving in the Canadian program for 12 years.
Very experienced, but not at this level yet.
Oh it's a good dive just a little bit of splash couldn't quite keep keep the splash down the start of the rip entry where you punch a hole in the water by grabbing the hands it looks as though he's going to disappear and then just as you see here a little bit of splash being thrown up it's a good dive it'll get eight and that certainly keeps his campaign for a medal alive
Keep saying it, hope I'm not going to put the mockers on him.
I like his consistency, I like his attitude, and I like the way he's performing tonight.
Excellent dive.
Eights across the board, takes him above Uze Liang.
And chances are he'll be in medal position at the end of this round.
In fact, he definitely will because Maxime Bouchard cannot overtake him at this stage.
as he can do in second place.
And to do that, he's basically got to get 10s.
And we've not seen too many of those.
Although Mr. Daley might have something to say about that when he steps up shortly.
Yeah, it's good.
He kept all the splash down.
Little bit soft in his lower back as he goes into the water.
So Max looking to pick up on the slightly faltering dive in the previous round, and that will help.
He'll only be in the early 70s, so 72, 73 with that one.
If he gets 7.5s and eights.
There are going to be calculations.
264.4, 7.5s and eight will count towards his total.
Round four this morning, Matt Mitchum, 67.20, which actually was his second lowest score.
His lowest coming on round five.
This is where it starts to swing.
One stage, Tom Daly was last in the prelims this morning.
Mitchum was leading the way for quite a while.
In with three and a half somersaults with Tuck, 3.2 for the 2008 Olympic champion.
Oh, he is not having a very good meet at all.
Mitchum is not on fire.
In fact, he's not even smoldering.
This is very, very weak from the 2008 Olympic champion.
He's been smashing it in training and he just isn't, he hasn't found his groove.
Wow.
So he's going to be battling for, you know, to hold on to his potential silver here.
You can see Normie smiling, happy.
yeah that's more of a forced wave and a smile isn't it well he's happy it's the jazz hands but look at the jazz hands there because that's emulating what he did this morning and that chasm between him and tom daly opens up but but this we're talking about the big one being his second round die once his bogey died which he did okay on but this
This morning he set into the stratosphere.
101.75.
Twice he went over 100 this morning in consecutive dives.
This was the first of them.
You wait for the roof to come off here.
It's a listed building, so hopefully it doesn't.
Forward four and a half somersaults with Tuck.
Go Tom.
It's not as good as this morning, but it's plenty good enough for him to stay in the lead 3.7 degree of difficulty forward four and a half somersaults in the tuck position Tom waiting pikes out.
He's got a great takeoff on that
As we saw this morning, he sailed over 100 points.
This will be close to 80, maybe just over 80 points.
But you know what?
There isn't really a competition going on at the moment.
Tom is way out in front.
Mitcham not really featuring.
I don't think even Matt's in the top three, is he?
He's not.
And Tom Daley, a bit like Jack Law in the prelims of three meter, is miles ahead of everybody else.
And this is the final when it counts.
320.45.
Look at that.
Nearly 30 marks separating him and Vincent Rien Do.
Good say Liang.
Matt Mitchum just holding on to the coattails of the medals.
Not in there yet.
James Denny in eighth.
Matt Dixon in ninth.
And Siddharth Bhadeshi in eleventh for India.
Looking good for Tom Daley.
Looking very good indeed.
He won't anoint him yet with that gold medal.
This is too big a dive for
Matthew Mitcham, including his last one, which he got 86 on.
But, boy, he's got some ground to make up.
Pardeschi.
Forward, two and a half semisaults, one twist.
That is the best dive we've seen from Pardeschi.
Certainly on this dive, sometimes has a bit of trouble with his twist.
wobbles around but this one he manages his feet aren't quite pointed are they they've got one pointed and one half pointed crossed over a little bit so he's a little bit
Rough around the edges.
He's straight up and down.
He's holding his triceps, so he's saying that he's in a bit of pain.
I'm not in the least bit surprised, having seen what he's put himself through today, not talking about the competition this morning and tonight, but really standing in between times.
He basically kept getting back on that 10 meter board and doing it until he got it right.
It's not really surprising his body is starting to break down a little bit.
He did compete earlier in the week as well.
Fifth round dive.
Matt Dixon is acquitting himself very, very well indeed.
The 14 year old from Plymouth.
British champion this year.
I mean, he got 400 marks and not at school either.
Back three and a half somersaults with tuck 3.3 for the Devonian.
Oh, nice.
Just a little over rotation.
It's a big dive for him.
3.3.
Starting backwards.
Swinging the arms above the head.
Looking at where you've been, not where you're going.
Kicking his feet up towards the 10 meter.
Just a little bit too high.
Throwing a bit of splash up.
That's still, that's probably better than he did this morning.
Let me just check.
Yes, he only got fives on this this morning.
That'll be 6.5s.
Good work, Maddie Dee.
Good work indeed, Maddie Dee.
Four years time when it gets to the Gold Coast.
It'll have filled out a bit, it'll have grown a bit.
They look a completely different competitor, but it's a fantastic experience.
We've had so many in Delhi who've come back and improved on their performances four years on.
QUE, seventh place.
Well, I've got to say three, four, five and six are very tightly bunched.
Somebody needs to jump out of the pack.
It's not too far back with two rounds to go.
three point four reverse three and a half somersaults with tuck for Chuyui.
Oh my goodness.
Now that is like being smacked around the back of the head by a baseball bat.
Ouch.
So it's all okay until now.
He doesn't quite get his hands back and oh, it just collapses into the water.
The water can feel like your arms are being ripped out from the sockets.
In fact, I had four reconstructive shoulder surgeries in my career diving from the 10 meter.
I hope Chewie doesn't need to book himself in for one.
Well, his body folded up like one of your deck chairs there as he went into the water.
Like he kind of half his body, met the other half of his body going in there.
I think there's a few people at home who have just recoiled.
It's like watching Doctor Who when you're a young kid.
You're behind the sofa after that, aren't you?
Dominic Bedgood of Australia.
Now, who wants to get into these medal positions?
We're not assuming Tom Daly's won it just yet, but we are looking at those who might push for silver and bronze.
He's fifth, and this is the big one.
You saw Daly do pretty well on recently.
Only three men are doing it.
Forward, four and a half.
Oh, that's good from Bedgood.
That's OK. A little bit of splash being thrown up.
So he needs to squeeze into his tuck shape a little bit more.
He's losing it.
But he's a little scrappy, but he gets it on his head.
It is 3.7, so it's worth a lot because mathematically the scores multiplied by the degree of difficulty.
OK, 68.
Well, I haven't been for that splash.
You'd be looking at 80s, but 68.4.
Walsh, I bet you think you're home.
That looks really good, but that splash kind of gives it away a little bit.
But he goes to go into the lead with Lee, Denny, Saint Liang, Riando, Bouchard, Mitchell, and of course, our runaway leader at the moment, Tom Daley to come.
Back to the arm stands.
Haven't seen one of these for a while.
Arm stand back, double somersaults, one and a half twists.
He's off.
He's off and he's in and he disappears.
Everything he needs in the dive.
Good, strong takeoff.
One and a half twists.
Double somersault.
And a good entry into the water.
Didn't hang around long, did he?
No, he didn't.
No, I wasn't quite ready for that commentary, but I got it out in the end.
Hopefully it made sense.
Why change the habit of lifetime?
Sevens.
67 for Li Fenyang.
Yeah, I don't think we're going to see him on the medal podium later on.
Although Sevens was OK, to be honest, when he didn't seem totally under control with that.
Not holding back the senior English divers here.
Your 3.3 in answers or your 3.0.
Let's go for a 3.6 in the mix and see what happens.
James Steny has done just that.
And of course, this was spot on.
Eighth place can be translated into something much, much better.
Back two and a half, two and a half twists.
You have seen this before.
It's Tom Daly's earlier dive that actually was OK today.
Oh, it's good from Denny.
3.6, two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists in the pike position.
Great strong takeoff, good leg extension, helicopter feet.
So the judges all came in for that.
This could have got eights, maybe even an 8.5, but you've got to keep your legs together, your toes pointed, you can't be flipping your feet around like they're helicopter rotors.
Ooh, Denny, ooby-doo.
7.5s out of seven for
The Englishman from Leeds.
20 years of age, same age as Tom Daly.
27 to second at the moment.
Dixon Lee below him.
Well, that was still not quite where he can be.
Let's say Liang is kind of profiting from other people around him not doing what they should do.
So that's why he finds himself in third.
But something Canadian is going to have
something to say about that and Matt Mitchum probably eventually to reverse three and a half or just just just manages to hang on to that we're watching him in training and he's been a little bit here and there that is short shorter vertical but it's tight it's good form and so he's probably going to sneak sevens from the judges that'll keep him in contention for a medal Utsiliang one dive to go
Trying to get the calculators out.
This is going to get very tight because those chasing Daly are grouped together very closely, although that's a 19-point advantage for Ute Liang over Bedgood.
Sevens across the board, 71.4.
Vincent Royandol.
Somebody pointed out to me that does that mean no water?
or words of that effect in French, which doesn't seem quite right for a diver, does it?
This is 3.3.
Now he is second place at the moment.
Oh, that's going to, well, what's that going to do?
Is that going to help or hinder?
So it's OK.
It's above average.
It's a big dive.
So we're going to see a couple of these in a row now.
This one for Vincent.
Max is going to follow.
Then Mitcham has downgraded his back three and a half pike to a back three and a half tuck.
so this is only going to get sevens which means it'll be less than 70 points will he bunch up with oopsie liang i think he will yes precisely what he has done it's got a two and a half point lead over the malaysian and that is nothing going into the last round at all that's certainly not a lead you can protect maxime bouchard might just have um fallen away from a
a medal push, but you never know.
He gets 90.
He goes in behind his Canadian colleague on this back three and a half somersaults with tuck.
Exactly the same dive you've just seen.
Oh, he's done well.
He's just a little bit low on the water, losing it on the takeoff.
Not quite powerful enough, not generating enough spin speed.
So he needs to get his arms through and extend a little bit more through the legs.
So as you can see here, just arching as he gets in.
It's clean and tidy, but he will drift now away from the medals.
Yeah, I think he's got too much to make up now.
He is 25 points behind Yutai Liang, 28 points behind his teammate.
So not today for a medal for Maxime Bouchard.
Continuing with giving you a little heads up on this morning's performance compared to tonight.
This was actually Matthew Mitchum's worst time in terms of marks.
Worth mentioning he's changed it.
So he's gone from a 2.6 degree of difficulty, a back three and a half pike to this, a back three and a half somersaults in the tucked position, 3.3.
Yeah, 52.2 he picked up this morning.
That's what he does now.
Much better than it was this morning.
Obviously, it's a different dive.
He's playing safe I think he's left himself too much to do to challenge Tom for the gold, but he is having to fight for this silver Will that be enough to get him closer?
to the Canadian and to the Malaysian
It's okay, but it's not good enough.
I've seen him score straight 10s on this dive.
He's short vertical there.
He's going to struggle to get a medal.
That would be a turn up for the books.
Wouldn't it just?
Third at the moment.
We're daily still to come.
So Huyen Dou and Uze Liang are likely medalists right now.
But the star turn, the class act tonight.
So often we have seen him beat
The world champion from Rome, 2009, bronze medalist from London, 2012, Thomas Robert Daley.
Back three and a half semisaults with Mike.
One of those high tariff dives.
Got over 100 on this this morning.
Oh, it's incredible!
Tens!
Right, come on, judges.
You might as well.
That is perfect.
So, this is textbook.
This is Tom Daley pretty much diving for the gold.
If the judges don't give it a ten, well, I think that they're wrong.
This is perfection.
Hundred points.
Here we come.
Why don't you just join the Strictly Come Dancing judging panel there for a moment?
out of his seat in the stratosphere.
Leon Taylor has indeed with Tom Daly.
Well, sadly, those tens, or that's ten, does not count towards the title.
And the total, 9.5, 9.5, and 9.5 do.
So Daly looks like it's going to go over 500.
423.05.
Vincent de Glendol in second.
Look how tight it is, though, for the next two places.
And Matt Mitchum has a big dive at the end.
3.6.
Denny in seventh.
Matthew Dixon in eighth.
So you've noticed Tom Daley walking up the steps there, followed by his coach Jane.
There's been lots of questions.
Where's he going?
He's actually moving up, moving himself up to the dry land diving area where he'll prepare for the next dive.
There's crash mats out there.
He'll be preparing for each and every dive.
We enjoyed having him here.
I think he's enjoyed being here, though his body may not feel quite that way after this competition.
Siddharth Padeshi leaves his arm stand till the very end.
2.7, so it's not a big tariff dive, but you feel the creaking joints as he gets into the upright position.
Oh, he's off.
Yep, he's off.
He wants to get this competition done.
And he has.
So that's six dives.
He has hurt himself, though, on quite a few of his dives in training, but he is made of tough stuff.
That's it.
He can have a rest now.
Beautiful dive to finish.
Excellent entry into the water.
Doesn't really hold his arm stand long enough, so the judges will penalise him.
He'd have got sevens if he'd held his arm stand.
Well done, Siddharth Parideshi.
258.30.
Give us a wave.
Yeah, thank you.
Two Indian divers here.
And I think he's going to need a few cushions on the way back on that plane just to support his aching body.
Huge cheer once again for the little man.
It's going to look very different in four years time is Matthew Dixon.
Can you imagine being 14, being pint sized and doing a forward two and a half somersaults with one twist.
That's the view that Matthew Dixon has and what he's about to do.
Oh, he's really gone for it.
He actually landed on the head of the 10 meter board, had my headphones off and he went, doing, he pushed so much effort into it.
Pops up into the air, just a little bit of an over rotation.
One twist into the two and a half somersaults, just drifting over a vertical.
What a performance from this young boy.
Three six six, great work.
Yeah, we'll see more of him.
European champs shows going over the world champs next year and the Olympics in Rio almost certain to be part of the GB team.
What can change in two years of diving though injuries and illness and stuff like that.
But I think we'll see him competing in Rio in a couple of years time.
A lot of promise shown by this young man as well, but hasn't quite been realized this evening.
Final round for Chuyue.
3.2 in the pike position and back two and a half somersaults, one and a half twists.
This is how he finishes off a very arduous week, actually.
He's had a lot of diving.
Yeah, it's a tidy finish from Chuyue.
with one and a half twists, so only 3.2 degree of difficulty.
The next diver, Dominic Beckgood, will add a twist to this dive, making it even more complex and earning an extra 0.4 degree of difficulty.
So this is good from Chu Yue, just rolling over.
He's had a pretty steady performance today.
Will finish outside of the medals, but he's dived in absolutely every competition available, and he's due a rest.
And now he can.
7.57, 68.8.
And it's going to finish below Matthew Dixon.
Dominic Bedgood.
What kind of top and tail in terms of his best performances from this morning.
Great opening.
Not a bad finish.
Fifth place.
Now what's he need to get up there?
Really needs mid-80s, high 80s, preferably on this 3.6.
Back two and a half, two and a half twists.
He gets 90 or so.
Good push for a medal.
Yeah, he's a good twister.
Didn't quite finish the dive off.
He's landing very similar to Tom, but for different reasons.
So, Tom likes to take off his good twist very, very quickly.
Just needs to squeeze into the pike shape a little bit longer to straighten out as he goes in.
It's high risk, high degree of difficulty.
Didn't quite work out for the young Australian.
now there's a good start a good finish this morning not a good finish in the evening that's why he's a bit down on his uh total mark doesn't make 400 this time around three nights seven five five and his medal chances have disappeared so lee
Three and Doe, Bouchard and Mitchum, all doing this dive in the last round.
In place four, the coach from Wellington, who decided after retiring a few years ago, he's going to come back into the sport and has done just that.
It's a beautiful dive to finish from Lee.
He's done a lot of diving as well.
Great.
Vertical entry into the water.
Hardly any splash.
Here's one and a half twist.
Two and a half somersaults.
Moving away from the diving board a little bit.
I think that's a good entry.
Maybe we'll get some eights from the judges.
Couple of falters early in his program, so he won't break 400.
Now about 20 points shy.
Just over.
Yes, of course.
72.
Okay, James Denny, what can you do for us on your biggest dive?
It's only three minutes doing this.
James Denny is doing it.
Tom Daly did it.
Now he needs 95, he's going to get eight and a half, nearly nines to go top.
Is he capable of that?
20 year old from Leeds, wouldn't put it past him.
Nice, okay, it's pretty good.
He did an absolute beauty next to Tom yesterday.
This is the dive that got them way out of, well, way out of trouble, really.
They were way off the pace in the synchro.
Murphy and Tom just not quite straightening out into the water there.
You can see he'll probably get six niles from the judges.
Just straightening out a little bit more, a bit less splash.
He'd have been eight and that would have been a huge score.
So just under 400 in total.
Reviewing it, going over it with his coach.
Obviously nothing much can be done about it this time, but when they get back on that 10-meter platform again, and AD will know how to resolve that problem.
The problem it is with Tse Liang of Malaysia.
If you want to look at the rankings, he's there in third place.
Doesn't seem to have shifted from that third place the last few rounds.
So what's it going to take to get him in first place?
in this 3.2 in with three and a half 68 or just over a seven average.
We'll get him at the top of the board with four more to go.
It's a beauty from Uti Liang.
Is that going to be good enough for the bronze?
He won the gold in the three-meter individual, beating Jack Law, much to many people's surprise.
He's been diving out of his skin.
He has saved his best till last.
He didn't do very well in the prelims on this.
Wow.
This will be close.
The pressure's on.
Will that be good enough for Silva, though?
Mitchum's still to dive.
Well, Mitchum's got a big dive.
Rien Do has a big dive.
Danny will have very little to do.
Just complete the dive.
It's pretty much his gold medal.
He won't be thinking along those lines of course now.
75 will put Riendo in the lead.
So eights here and the Canadian, I think is good as, has a medal.
He'll be aware of that.
He'll be taking just a little bit more time over this one.
Very smooth, very precise, great entry.
That's all he can do.
He's 3.2, needs to make it count.
So to beat Yuzilang, he needs eight.
Will that be good enough?
It's going to be pretty tight.
I don't know, a little bit short.
The vertical as he goes into the water.
Great list of dives from the Canadian, only 17 years old.
Yeah, such a shame.
Yeah, he will be back.
I think we are seeing somebody who's going to grow.
in every respect in terms of his quality.
I think we'll see a far more bulked up reindeer next time in Commonwealth Games competition.
Maxime Bouchard facing these tents if he's going to get into third place.
And obviously Daley still to come.
Mitchum still to come.
So the medal will pass Maxime Bouchard by today.
It's a tough one to finish on, too, even though the tariff's not very high.
3.2.
Back two and a half with one and a half twists.
They've seen it a few times before.
Yeah, a little bit off the pace.
Yeah, just holding his elbow there.
Just shows you how much these divers have to endure, hitting the water at nearly 35 miles an hour plus every time.
Just so hard on the body.
It's quite hard on the brain as well by the time we get to this time of night, isn't it?
Seven and seven point fives for Maxime Bouchard.
All right, now we are down to the last two and this was worth eighty six point four this morning for Matthew Mitchum.
If he does that now, he will get the silver medal.
If he does anything under eighty two,
It's the bronze medal.
So a fluctuation of five points would make a lot of difference here.
Same dive, but this time in the pike position, which means it's a 3.6 rather than 3.2.
Yeah, it's about two and a half somersaults, two and a half twists.
That's where the extra 0.4 comes from.
I don't think that's good enough for the silver.
I think that will only be good enough just for the bronze.
But let's see, it's 3.6.
He's left himself a bit too much to do.
Maybe that won't even get a medal.
Let's have a look at this.
Two and a half twists, two and a half somersaults.
He's thrown up too much splash.
If he doesn't get more than sevens, he's not in the medals.
What a turn up for the books.
He is not.
The 2008 gold medalist from Beijing and the silver medalist from four years ago has had, well, a difficult four years since India.
Just well documented in his book.
He's back.
We thought this morning he might be back to his best.
He isn't.
He's not going to get a medal.
This is a demonstration dive now for Tom Daly because he needs 10 points.
He won't be seeing it like that.
They want to go out with a flourish.
He wants to get over 500 marks.
That's his territory.
That's his domain.
And this is the final dive for Tom Daley for gold at the Commonwealth Games.
There you go.
Outstanding from Tom Daley, retaining his Commonwealth Games title.
He won four years ago in Delhi.
Here he is again in Glasgow, winning by an absolute country mile.
He'll go way over 500 points, 90 plus for this one.
Even with the challenges he's had in the prelim, the questions around what he's been doing, he silenced his critics.
Gold for Daley.
Well, just a round off the numbers.
Two nines and a 9.5 to count towards the total.
There's his new coach from London.
Wow.
Tom Daley has done that with absolute precision.
He is not that anybody gets
within touching distance on him.
Massive chasm between one and two.
Just look at this.
I'll tell you exactly what you need to know.
5.16.55 for Daley.
And then the others were scrapping for second and third.
Scrapping best for Silva.
We would say Liang to add to his gold from three meter.
And Vincent Riendoux of Canada picking up the bronze.
Matthew Dixon.
Watch out for him in four years time in ninth place.
But the truth is, it's a broken record.
The truth is, it's a broken record.
Ladies and gentlemen, please take your seats and make sure you give a big warm welcome to our medallists, which is the medal ceremony coming up very soon.
My name is Kerry Dixie and I'm a designer and designer for the class of 2014 at the University.
I'm Paul Hutchis.
I'm the original designer of the model that I take for trees, for meadows and for kicks.
My name is Paul Hutchis and I designed meadows for the class of 2014.
We decided to use silk for the dress and print one piece of silk because it's summer and a lot of the likes are dressed up like we're in traditional custom.
So it presented quite a big challenge.
She collaborated with the Centre for Red Vars Textiles and they helped us print out every single pattern piece which we then cut out and the tailor needed a dress from that.
We've used palace tweed which is my favourite fabric which has been hand woven up on the head of these, especially for this project.
I just knew that you could produce the most tactile, beautiful, bang on brands, gifts that glasses would offer.
We have wood that I've been storing for up to 15 years.
These are wood that's so beautiful they couldn't get used, but anything that became an understanding joke.
It's completely unorthodox to put a ducky great big shaped lump of nature onto a finely tuned machine.
However, we do have a big bertha with the planer, and she can handle it.
They're sawing the planes to the standard lift block sizes, then the blocks right onto a series of three and a half minutes.
It's moving fast, and you'd say so, and you get an even coat all the way around.
The train very much has semi-rich design in relation to it.
I had to keep the consistency of the metal design, and my job in this is to keep that concept alive.
The medals go through a very complicated 15-part process.
The only way that we work as sort of jewelers and if we were a small team is, you know, that's an ideal fraction of the way, and just working the medals by hand.
The wax is made AMO, which is then cast into metal.
And then there's a process of cleaning them up before finishing the polish up.
And they take about, I'll say about three days to make each one.
That's sort of the fun of it, I think.
For us, it was about making something that had blood, sweat and tears, like half a week's after on the train.
I don't think it's going to hit me, actually, until I'm out there in the stadium.
It's going to be a real kind of strange tingly moment, I think.
Like gemstones, if you treat them the right way, to the right stages, they are absolutely beautiful.
I think that they are sitting up there waiting for this, and I really honestly do.
Talks about Glasgow, talks about a heritage, and the fact that Glasgow is a city that does things in a different way.
the the
I don't know.
Thank you.
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the medal ceremony for the Women's 3D to Springboard.
The medals will be presented by Chief Communications Officer, Glasgow 2014, Gordon Arthur.
Accompanied by venue competition manager, Royal Commonwealth Pool, Edinburgh, Craig Cunningham.
The winner of the bronze medal, representing England, Hannah Starling.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
The winner of the silver medal representing Canada, Jennifer Abel.
medallist and Commonwealth champion with a score of 347.25 representing Australia, Esther Chin.
Ladies and gentlemen, the National Anthem of Australia.
.
Let's go, let's celebrate our four of our game's winners.
Everybody's saving, if you didn't know anyone You still make some good friends, that's the way it ends When I have myself a drink, I'll drink Cause the sunshine wants to live
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
Thank you very much.
I'm so ready to leave
Thank you.
You.
so
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the medal ceremony for the men's turkey to bark for.
The medals will be presented by Chief Communications Officer, Pasco 2014, Gordon Arthur.
Accompanied by Secretary General of the Commonwealth Games Association Scotland, Fiona McEwan.
The winner of the bronze medal, representing Canada, Vysolyan Dao.
Well, it could be the first of many medals at an international level.
Commonwealth Games for the 17-year-old from Quebec, Vincent Heliendo.
429.25, beating the likes of Matthew Metcham, Maxime Bouchard.
into fourth and fifth, and there's a big smile to accompany that bronze medal.
He's pretty much in the top three all the way through and finally made a step up to second in the end by about four points, four and a half points to be more precise.
Ute Liang adds a silver medal in the 10 meter to the gold in the three meter.
Good work for him and a good week for him.
but with marks of 94, 64, a bit low, 81, 79, 102.6 and 93.50.
It was in the competition, it was a procession for Tom Daly.
Daly was going to win a gold medal more easily than that in international competition, so he had to do it.
He's got autopilot and terrific, really terrific.
People can knock.
People can chide.
People can say he does too much stuff outside the ball.
Well, there's the perfect answer for you.
516.55.
So it is gold once again for Tom Daley.
I'm sorry.
The Olympic bronze medalist is the 10-meter platform champion for the second time round at the Cold War Games.
Backing up what he did in Delhi in 2010.
2014, a repeat, an even bigger margin this time, not over Matthew Mitchum, over Utse Liang, and Vincent Riando of Canada with the bronze.
Ladies and gentlemen, boys and girls, I hope you've enjoyed the diving event, and it's the final day of diving at the C20 Commonwealth Games.
Congratulations, of course, to the winners in the men's park for a top day league of England, Coyote, Leanne, Malaysia, and Vincent Ferrando, Canada.
In the women's event, congratulations to Australia's annual gold medalist, Esther Chin, silver medal to the Canada's.
Jennifer Abel, and Bronzell to Elins and Stirling.
Congratulations to everyone.
Happy to be inspired by what you have seen here at Glasgow 2014.
To make a positive change to your health and well-being, visit www.nbks.co.uk for a crash at Glasgow 2014.
Three years old, Glasgow.
The organizing committee would like to thank all firefighters for their time and dedication toward making today's event such a success.
Without your hard work, these amazing games and memories would not be possible.
Ladies and gentlemen, that concludes this session at the Royal Commonwealth Hall.
On behalf of the Commonwealth Games Federation, I'd like to thank the 2014 Organizing Committee for the Commonwealth Games.
We hope you have enjoyed your day today.
Thank you for being part of Halfway 2014.
Before you go, have a quick look around to make sure you have all your bits and bobs and have a very safe journey.
It's Christmas magic.
Have a safe journey home and enjoy the rest of the games.
Thank you for being part of these games and for supporting all the athletes.